<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ionah's contestation about his gourd In a sermon deliuered at Pauls Crosse. Septemb. 19. 1624. By R.V. preacher of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>Vase, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119027</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854234</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19643</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19643)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1042:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ionah's contestation about his gourd In a sermon deliuered at Pauls Crosse. Septemb. 19. 1624. By R.V. preacher of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>Vase, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] L[egat] for Robert Bird, and are to be sold at his shoppe, at the signe of the Bible in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.V. = Robert Vase.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IONAH'S CONTESTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION ABOVT HIS GOVRD.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON DELIVERED AT <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 19. 1624.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. V.</hi> Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IONAH 4. verſ. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And God ſaid to <hi>IONAH,</hi> Doeſt thou well to be angry for the gourd? and he ſaid, I doe well to be angry, even vnto death.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>Robert Bird,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe, at the ſigne of the Bible in Cheape-ſide. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS AVDLEY ESQVIER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, Conſidering with my ſelfe the over-flowing fancies of theſe daies, the deſire beeing growne common vnto each man almoſt, to ſee himſelfe in Print (wherein is obſervable much vanity vnder the Sunne) it was not my purpoſe from the beginning, to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, further then by publiſhing with open voyce, theſe my poore indigeſted labours: and if by adventuring into the light, I be equally cenſured to fall vnder the ſame taxation which I have laide vpon the times, it would proove but an addition to my vaine attempts to lay the imputation vpon other mens perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>Thus far notwithſtanding in this last particular, I muſt not diſſemble; that reading the counſell of a faithfull friend, who hath iudiciouſly cenſured the Diſeaſes of the time, and in the firſt place doth note ſuch who love to write every thing, and ſuch who affect to write nothing, thing, I inclined to his reaſons, and then overcome well-nigh
<pb facs="tcp:19643:3"/>with a ſelfe conceit and loue of my owne inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I began to perſwade with my ſelfe, that the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe halfe-conceived, might bee produced really into effect.</p>
            <p>This one thing in ſerious wiſe, yet faintingly vnder the ſilent langvage of my pen, I doe pronounce, how full of <hi>Interiections,</hi> the ſtudie of this Theme was which Sermon-wiſe I have vnfolded: ſo why may I not againe without ſuſpicion of ſelfe flattery preſume, that in the ſame, I have not travelled altogether in vaine? but as I diſcovered ſome ſparkle of new light to the ſetling of the peace of my owne ſoule, ſo I truſt the peruſall hereof ſhall not proove vngratefull to others, who ſtudy after pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to pleaſe the Lord with vprightneſſe in the land of the living.</p>
            <p>Why with you Sir, rather then others, I have deſired to leave this ſimple gage of my hearty regard and ſincere affection, I muſt confeſſe, that friendly vſage and kinde reſpect continued ſince the time you firſt had ſight of mee beyond my merit, and the ordinary vſe to ſtrangers, hath made me not only hold in reverence your liberall diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this way; but alſo to advance my thoughts higher in a ſpeciall regard vnto Divine providence, with patience to expect the iſſue in this and other occurrents, whereof vnto my promiſed content in private, I have made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular application, and vnder this name doe crave par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for my boldneſſe if I have erred.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Rachel</hi> had borne <hi>Naphtali,</hi> ſhee expreſſed the travell of her ſoule, by the name ſhee beſtowed vpon the fruit of her body; ſhee had wraſtled with much paine in her inward deſires before ſhe could bring forth, therefore ſhe gave the childes name from wraſtling, ſhe called him <hi>Naphtali. Iacob</hi> wraſtled with God and prevailed; and
<pb facs="tcp:19643:3"/>thence is the name beſtowed vpon all Gods Elect; he is no childe of Iſrael that is no wraſtler.</p>
            <p>Whither it be with our fleſh and blood, or in an higher kinde, with Principalities and Powers, or in the higheſt degree with God himſelfe, with teares and prayers and ſtrong cries, and other whiles with pangs and terrors, with griefe, with anger, anguiſh, and bitterneſſe of ſpirit, we muſt all that looke for the bleſsing wraſtle the wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of God.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> wraſtled a long time before he obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Iſaac; Iſaac</hi> wraſtled twentie yeeres before he obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> by his wraſtling got the name of Iſrael: <hi>Rachel</hi> was a woman-wraſtler when ſhe brought forth <hi>Naphtali,</hi> an example to inſtruct her weaker Sexe in the like trade of wrastling, and <hi>Hanna</hi> did ſuſtaine a long and grievous wraſtling; yet in the end ſhee had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with God, and brought forth <hi>Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Ionah</hi> was a wrastler, and ſo am I: Further to expreſſe which, then to the common Reader I doe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, for whoſe ſake chiefely, I have enlarged thoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, which were vttered lately in a great aſſembly, have collected them into one forme, and doe now make humble offer of them to your gentle intertainment. The which kinde of teſtimonie of my ſincere meaning and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious loue profeſſed to you, I have rather made choice of, then as the vſuall manner now adaies is, to prefixe a large Encomium of titles, honours, words of Worſhip and of Worth, termes of the higheſt elevation, and ſtraines of the loweſt and most proſtrate ſubmiſsion, with many other ſuperlative peereleſſe, compariſons, and farre fetcht com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, and to place it in the front of their writings in a forme Dedicatory, to give luſtre to all the pages fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb facs="tcp:19643:4"/>whether to the Lords or Ladies, Patrones or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troneſſes.</p>
            <p>Which kinde of writing, as it was never practiſed by mee, ſo Sir I hope, you doe preſume, the ſame not to bee affected by you; whoſe retired integritie and vnſhaken conſtancy, in the ſtricteſt courſe of mortification doth well witneſſe, that you more reſpect the praiſes of God then of men. For which cauſe I have the more heartily deſired an increaſe of your good opinion towards mee, and an happy confirmation of that bond of mutuall good liking, whereof I have ſeene ſome faire beginnings.</p>
            <p>Accept Sir then of this my kindneſſe, the fruits of a ready minde, the pledge of my love and true obſervance only as it reſpecteth you; a testification of my good will to Sion, and the building vp vnto further holineſſe, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſptcteth others not yet growne, but groaning vnder their imperfections; a fruit of my inward labours &amp; ſtrivings, my <hi>Naphtali,</hi> my <hi>Benoni,</hi> pained as I was in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, grieved in the production, &amp; after, as reſpecte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th my ſelfe and halting yet hopefull indeavours in the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of his Church. And ſo I commend it and my ſelfe once more to your friendly acceptance, and your counſels, wiſhes, and whole ſelfe to his happie guydance, who is God of all true comfort and conſolation to his choſen Iſrael, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>An vnfained lover of your Perſon, a ſtudious obſerver of your Worſhip:</hi> R. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ionah's</hi> Meditation vnder his Arbour.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TOſs't by Sea, by Land distreſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> here hath found ſome reſt,</l>
               <l>When others live in houſes ſeel'd</l>
               <l>My bed and boade is in the field.</l>
               <l>What care I then? ſo I may have</l>
               <l>The comfort which of God I crave.</l>
               <l>Heare Lord, O heare now my requeſt,</l>
               <l>Then is thy ſervant <hi>Ionah</hi> Bleſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Advice to <hi>Ionah.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>What though with wealth ſome doe abound;</l>
               <l>Content, it ſprings not from the ground,</l>
               <l>A little to the iuſt is bleſt,</l>
               <l>When great revenewes are accurſt:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhall be conſum'd</l>
               <l>Which of her glory hath preſum'd.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Ionah</hi> thou art ignorant,</l>
               <l>A ſelfe-will'd man and male-content,</l>
               <l>Who meaſureſt the Lords decree</l>
               <l>According to thy fantaſie.</l>
               <l>Therefore thou art now ſad, now glad,</l>
               <l>Whence is this mutabilitie?</l>
               <l>The Lord the ſame, our nature's bad</l>
               <l>He changeth not, though chang'd be we:</l>
               <l>Then doe thy office, but conſider</l>
               <l>The Gourd that ſpring's from'th ground will wither.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19643:5"/>
            <head>IONAH'S CONTESTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION ABOVT HIS GOVRD. IN A SERMON DELIVERED AT <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 19. 1624.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IONAH 4. verſ. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And God ſaid to <hi>IONAH,</hi> Doeſt thou well to be angry for the gourd? and he ſaid, I doe well to be angry, even vnto death.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS whole Propheſie or Booke of <hi>Ionah,</hi> may well for the ſtate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be ſo conceived, as to be borne forth by way of Dialogue or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlocution betweene the Lord and Him: the Argument maintained ſometimes directly, ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly; by Word, by Signe, by Practiſe, by Example.</p>
            <p>The Lord begins: The word of the Lord came vnto <hi>Ionah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amittai,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ionah</hi> anſweres diſobediently. The Lords ſends him to one place, hee goeth to another.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19643:6"/>Then the Lord ſpeaketh againe, but by his creatures, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his practiſe againſt <hi>Ionah's,</hi> and maintaines his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument by the Windes, the Marriners, the Whale-fiſh; and ſo the controveſie deſcendeth into the bottome of the Sea.</p>
            <p>At the third Chapter; Behold, A new Scaene of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beginneth. The word of the Lord came vnto <hi>Ionah</hi> the ſecond time; ſaying, Ariſe, Goe vnto Nineveh that great Citie, and Preach vnto it, the preaching that I bid thee.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Ionah</hi> anſweres like an obedient ſeruant, confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his practiſe to the Lords command.</p>
            <p>But ſoone after (his Meſſage, according to the tenour thereof, not taking effect) he ſhowes his diſcontented minde; and the ſame expreſſed in angry tearmes, inwardly concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by way of expoſtulation, in the beginning of the fourth Chapter.</p>
            <p>Then the Lord enters parley with <hi>Ionah,</hi> after a friendly manner, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry?</hi> the Lord replies vpon <hi>Ionah</hi> by a loving ſigne, and the Lord prepared a gourd, &amp;c. and thereof <hi>Ionah</hi> was exceeding glad.</p>
            <p>But now, <hi>Iterum ſaeuiunt irae;</hi> Anger breakes out againe: The gourd withers, <hi>Ionah</hi> frets; the Lord ſpeakes, <hi>Ionah</hi> anſweres; the one friendly as before, the other frowardly: Ionah, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry?</hi> yea ſaith <hi>Ionah, I doe well to bee angry, even vnto death.</hi> The next words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the prophefie and whole diſputation directly againſt <hi>Ionah:</hi> And thus may be conceived the frame and ſtructure of the whole Booke.</p>
            <p>This Text is a plaine part of the Dialogue, diſputation, conteſtation, or contention (which you will); and herein more particularly are obſerueable, the parties contending, the Lord and <hi>Ionah:</hi> the manner how the contention or controverſie is carryed, and it is by word, or ſaying: God ſaid to <hi>Ionah,</hi> and againe <hi>Ionah</hi> ſaid to God.</p>
            <p>The matter in queſtion is expreſſed in the word, <hi>angry,</hi> and therein I ſhall ſpeake of anger ſomewhat largely: the queſtion in ſpeciall, is concerning <hi>Ionah</hi> his anger, and therein I ſhall deale more ſtrictly. And thus far on the Lords part.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19643:6"/>
            <p> The anſwere of <hi>Ionah</hi> hath likewiſe in it theſe three ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, anſwerable to the three parts of the former <hi>Quere,</hi> which may eaſily bee apprehended in the queſtion by the Lord, ſpecially directed to <hi>Ionah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, here is a ſimple affirmation on <hi>Ionah's</hi> part, the Lords queſtion firſt implying thus much, <hi>Ionah,</hi> art thou angry? yea, ſaith <hi>Ionah,</hi> I am angry: Secondly, a peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory affirmation or iuſtification, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry Ionah?</hi> yea, <hi>I doe well to be angry.</hi> Thirdly, a deepe aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Doest thou well to be angry for the gourd?</hi> yea, <hi>I doe well to be angry vnto death.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="circumstance">
               <head>The firſt Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>The parties contending are the Lord, and <hi>Ionah. Impar congreſſus,</hi> a moſt vnequall match: and yet <hi>Ionah</hi> farre the weaker, hath alſo the weaker cauſe in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tu domine fundaſticaelos,</hi> Thou Lord in the beginning haſt eſtabliſhed the heavens, and laide the foundation of the earth, and formed the ſpirit of man within him. Great is our God, and great is his power, his wiſedome is infinite.</p>
               <p>Now looke vpon <hi>Ionah,</hi> and who or what is he? at the beſt, but a weake and mortall creature, a man borne of a woman, of few dayes and full of miſery; hee commeth vp and is cut down like a flower, he fleeth as a ſhadow and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not. And doeſt thou open thine eyes vpon ſuch an one, bring ſuch one into iudgement with thee, ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> in the ſame place? Here is inſtruction for all in places of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority; let them learne from this one example of the Lord here, how to carry themſelues towards their inferiours.</p>
               <p>Doth the Lord vouchſafe to reaſon with <hi>Ionah,</hi> and give him account of his doings? who then art thou that doeſt ſwell againſt thy brother, and diſdaineſt to anſwere thy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſeruant?</p>
               <p>Drop downe yee heavens from above, and let the skies powre downe righteouſneſſe. Woe be to him that ſtriveth with his maker. For wee may not ſearch into the Lords counſell, further then he hath revealed (it is farre more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous then to meddle in mans matters) but there admire
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19643:7"/>where he hath concealed. Howbeit, we ſee (to the ſhame of our pride and ſcorne of our haughtie ſtomackes) the Lord full often doth not refuſe to commit himſelfe to the tryall; the Iudge to be iudged by vs his vaſſals: Therefore hath he appointed a day wherein he will iudge the world in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; and the conſciences of wicked men, who refuſe his iudgements now, ſhall be made to acknowledge his iuſtice then. Thus ſpeakes the Apoſtle: and he alleadgeth it out of the Pſalmes, that thou mighteſt be inſtified in thy ſayings, and overcome when thou art iudged.</p>
               <p>Let then all petty gods, take example from this great God, whether they be Kings or Rulers, or Magiſtrates, or Officers, or Maſters, or Fathers of Families; ſince God is equall towards vs, (and that the heavens will one day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) let vs learne equitie and faire dealing one towards another. This leſſon had <hi>Iob</hi> learnt Chap. 3.13. If I did deſpiſe the cauſe of Man-ſeruant, or Maide-ſeruant when they contended with mee, what ſhall I doe when God ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vp? and when hee viſiteth, what ſhall I anſwere him?</p>
               <p>Thus ſhall we walke worthy the title of Gods; otherwiſe, breake the teeth of the vngodly and malicious, ſmite out the Iaw-bones of the Lyons, O Lord.</p>
               <p>For ſuch, who walke not according to this rule, retaine no longer the image of their Maker; but are degenerated into Lyons, Beares, Tygers, evening Woolues, and ſo are they called in Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="circumstance">
               <head>The ſecond Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>Here the queſtion is, how the ſaying came to <hi>Ionah,</hi> againe how <hi>Ionah</hi> ſpake to the Lord. Was it <hi>facie ad faciem,</hi> face to face? not ſo. It was a Priviledge of <hi>Moſes</hi> alone, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. That the Lord would ſpeake to him face to face, and this but in a figure too; there being intended thereby, but only a more familiar kinde of preſence or dealing with <hi>Moſes,</hi> then with any other the Prophets, vntill Chriſt came: for when <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to ſee the glory of God, and his very countenance, it was permitted to him only, to haue a ſight of his Backe-parts while his glory paſſed by. This
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19643:7"/>being a received truth: That no man can ſee God and live, I meane the life of Nature; more then the waxe can indure the heate of the fire without melting.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe, neyther was it the voyce of the Lord proceeding immediately from his ſpirit, which ſpake to <hi>Ionah</hi> here, or to any of his Prophets elſewhere: For as no man hath ſeene his ſhape, ſo neyther hath any man heard his voyce at any time, as ſayth our Saviour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.37.</p>
               <p>The voyce of the Lord (ſayth <hi>David</hi>) is powerfull, the voyce of the Lord is full of maieſtie, &amp;c. but in his Temple doth everie man ſpeake of his glory. And truly, vnleſſe wee firſt take comfort in hearing the Lords voyce in his Temple, and that by the Miniſtery of man daily delivered, wee ſhall take little pleaſure in hearing the Lords owne voyce which ſhall ſhake both heaven and earth, much more the conſciences of all ſinners, when he ſhall ſhow himſelfe in farre more dreadfull manner then once he did vpon Mount Sinai.</p>
               <p>But how came the voyce to <hi>Ionah?</hi> I have ſhowen you negatively how not; was it then in audible manner from without? audible or rather intelligible it was to <hi>Ionah,</hi> but in ſecret and from within, like that ſtill ſmall voyce that came to <hi>Eliah.</hi> The Lord ſpake vnto <hi>Iob,</hi> but out of the whirl-winde, and <hi>Job</hi> therewith grew humbled, before a man moſt daring.</p>
               <p>And I thinke, had there to this voyce, in what kinde ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it came to <hi>Jonah,</hi> beene ioyned, but ſome powerfull ſigne of the Lords preſence, <hi>Ionah</hi> durſt not then have carryed himſelfe ſo petulantly, if the Lord had ſpoken to him; whither out of the whirlewinde, as to <hi>Iob;</hi> or out of the flaming buſh, as to <hi>Moſes;</hi> or out of the ſtorme, as to <hi>Eliah;</hi> or in a more excelling viſion as vnto <hi>Daniel,</hi> as vnto <hi>Iohn.</hi> Rev. 1. He durſt not then have replyed as he doeth, much leſſe (if, as he is, in his owne ineffable exiſtency had God ſpoken) durſt he once to have muttered.</p>
               <p>It is true, the Lord doeth ſometimes ſpeake audibly, ſtriking the outward ſenſe of man; as by the Trumpet which called vnto <hi>Iohn. Revel.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſometimes hee hath revealed himſelfe viſibly to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19643:8"/>the eye of mans body; and ſo he did to the young man, with <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet. 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.17. and to <hi>Paul. Actes</hi> the 9.3.</p>
               <p>Sometimes againe, and that very vſually vnder the time of the old Law, he hath revealed his will to the fantaſie, or imagination, and that by a dreame in the night.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, and that moſt ſpecially, and moſt inwardly, of all hath the Lord made knowen his purpoſe to the minde of man; his intellective or vnderſtanding part, as the moſt eſſentiall part of man, and moſt capable of Divine revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But this laſt hath not happened alwayes after one kinde and manner, but ſometimes after a more abſtracting and raviſhing ſort; the man for the preſent being ſo diſpoſed, that hee knowes not whether his ſpirit bee in or out of his body, at the leſtwiſe, the ſpirit being for the time deprived, the vſe of any the ſenſes, that it may attend the better to heavenly viſions.</p>
               <p>Thus was <hi>Ezekiel</hi> carryed out of himſelfe into the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of dry bones, <hi>Paul</hi> into the third heavens, thus fell <hi>Peter</hi> into his trance.</p>
               <p>Sometimes againe (to come to the queſtion in hand) and this moſt commonly to his Seruants the Prophets, the Lord hath given his word or his ſigne by a ſecret inſtinct or inſpiration.</p>
               <p>Thus was the manner of olde, and that thus it was with <hi>Ionah</hi> in this place may appeare by the context, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this ſpeech with the precedent verſe, where is ſet downe that <hi>Ionah</hi> fainting, wiſhed in himſelfe to die, and ſaid, it was better for him to die then live.</p>
               <p>This wiſh or ſpeech of <hi>Jonah</hi> was ſecret within himſelfe, no eare heard it but the Lord, and ſo the Lord in ſecret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine doth anſwer him, and hee againe anſwers to the Lord. The Lord ſaide to <hi>Ionah,</hi> and <hi>Ionah</hi> ſaide to the Lord: the manner and carriage of which ſaying, and interchange of ſpeech, as it was ſecret and ſilent, ſo no thoughts could vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand but the heart of <hi>Ionah,</hi> and the Lord only.</p>
               <p>Shall we now apply this? the Author to the Hebrewes, hath done it in theſe words; God who did in times paſt at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19643:8"/>times and ſundry waies ſpeake vnto the Fathers, the Prophets have in theſe laſt daies ſpoken to vs by his owne Sonne whom hee hath appointed heire of all things, by whom he made the worlds.</p>
               <p>Now which kinde of ſpeakings had you rather chooſe? whither by ſeruants in the houſe, or him that hath made the houſe and is heire of all. Some there be who ſay, O that we had lived in the daies of the Prophets, or the Prophets now in our daies, for then ſhould we be vifited with new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations and viſions from the Lord.</p>
               <p>Hence ſpring vp, almoſt in all ages, thoſe Anabaptiſticall ſpirits pretending daily, new revelations, but inſpired from hell, to leade away vnſtable ſoules, which will not content themſelues with the ſound doctrine of the Goſpel, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Chriſt Ieſus the only Sonne of God.</p>
               <p>To this end alſo have the Miniſters of Antichriſt deviſed new traditions and vnwritten verities to feed the humour of ſuch men, that they all might bee damned ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who beleeve not the truth, but have pleaſure in vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: in his ſecond Epiſtle to the Theſſalonians.</p>
               <p>O remember the ſaying before, that God ſpake divers times and diverſly to the Fathers, the Prophets; none of them, for the time, being able to deliver an abſolute forme of doctrine, but as expecting daily ſomethings yet to bee added, they waited for further revelations or inſpirations from above.</p>
               <p>And ſhall we expect that doctrine, which they left imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to be made vp or perfected, by the giddy ſpirits or furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous phantaſies, of ſuch who come like the old Prophets; I have dreamed, I have dreamed?</p>
               <p>O no, God hath ſpoken to vs in theſe laſt dayes by his Sonne, the heyre of all, who came out of his Fathers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and therefore hath revealed his whole will concerning our ſalvation and the means thereof; and the ſame to remaine without any addition, alteration, or change, to the end of the world: he hath alſo ſealed the ſame by the witneſſe of his ſpirit in the hearts of all beleevers, ſo that we may ſay with <hi>Peter,</hi> whether ſhall we goe from thee? for thou haſt the word of Life, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19643:9"/>
               <p> To conclude, ſince Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote his revelation which he received from Chriſt, there is to be looked for no other Revelation whether from Angels or men, but curſed is he that addeth or taketh away from the words of the Booke of this Propheſie, or from the writing of any other the Prophets, Euangeliſts, Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>This word of God ſaith, S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> is able to make the man of God perfect; what neede then any other helpe and furtherance, perfection being by this word to bee attained vnto; a perfection greater then that the fathers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, ſaw, a perfection ſo farre as is conuenient, during the ſtate of our mortall life and Pilgrimage here, vntill that glorious day in full ſtrength breake out, and the ſhadowes clearely be chaced away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="particular">
               <head>3. Particular.</head>
               <p>Anger in generall may bee defined, a commotion of the minde for ſome ſuppoſed evill, ioyned with an appetite of revenge.</p>
               <p>Let the parts be examined. I ſay, firſt a commotion for that it is not a ſimple affection but compounded of hate or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and hope; hate for ſome conceived iniury, &amp; hope to be revenged vpon the iniurer: yea it drawes the whole man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to commotion; the head deviſeth, the hand acteth, the feete cannot abide in one place but runne the paths of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; all the inward powers are like wiſe troubled: our love per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext, feare confuſed, deſires inflamed, our reaſon peruerted; and the whole man doth ſuffer paine together with the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and is diſordered. Therefore not vnfitly doe I call it a commotion.</p>
               <p>So alſo is it a commotion of the minde not of the humor, or complexions principall; it being the iudgement of Divines ſo likewiſe of true Phyloſopy, that the paſsions may bee occaſioned from the divers temperatures of the body, but doe proceede principally from the diſpoſition of the divine ſoule; according to the truth of this principle, that the ſoule is the prime moover in the body, and it were a thing mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and abſurd to affirme that the humours of the body have any power over the ſoule to worke vpon it contrary to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19643:9"/>its immortall and impasſible nature, impaſsible of any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſave onely from that hand which made and infuſed it.</p>
               <p>Beſides many arguments tending to which purpoſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this one for all, namely, that two the moſt principall affections gouerning in this life, loue and ioy are not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined together with the ending of the ſtory of our dayes, but doe accompany the ſoule, and are inherent in the ſame after, as without the expreſsion of which two there can bee no happineſſe; a cleare euidence that both the ſoule was the prime moover while it dwelt in the body, ſo that it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame power and that in a more noble kinde, when it is without the body.</p>
               <p>I adde this moreover, that it ariſeth from ſome ſuppoſed evill. For there is not alwayes a reall and ſubſiſting cauſe of our anger. The Pope was angry for his Peacocke, the Pope was angry for his Porke, and wee are often angry with our very ſhadowes.</p>
               <p>And laſtly I ſay, ioyned with an appetite of reuenge, and therefore wee ſee commonly at the firſt apprehenſion of any wrong, that the blood doeth recoyle vnto the heart, and by and by into the face; as a Blood-hound or Maſtiffe, to flie into the face of the iniurer.</p>
               <p>Among all the paſsions, by God planted in the nature of man, there is none more violent then that of anger; and for this cauſe truely, becauſe wee are by nature more impatient of euill, then we are coueting of good, made ſenſeleſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through the cloying exceſſe of preſent delights, but too quicke and ſenſible enough, euen of the leaſt ſuppoſed euill, where againſt anger doeth chiefely bend its force.</p>
               <p>It is nouriſhed with the moſt bitter humour; a bagge of gall hath angers food, it feedeth on the ſame with greedines, yet without all delight, and thirſteth after humane blood.</p>
               <p>It is a Serpent that eateth out her owne bowels; a wilde beaſt that ſcorneth to bee tamed; a ſacke full of poiſon; a fire pent vp within the bones; a flame when it breaketh out to conſume others.</p>
               <p>It is a ſickeneſſe of the Soule, a Frenzy, a Fury, a Madneſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19643:10"/>
                  <l>Ora tument ira, nigreſcunt ſanguine venae:</l>
                  <l>Lumina Gorgonia ſaevius angue micant.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The lips ſwell, the blood turnes blacke within the veines; The eyes more firie red, then are Gorgonian Snakes.</p>
               <p>What, have not Poets and heathen Moraliſts, written in the reproach and diſpraiſe of anger? Let him that is angry, before hee ſtrike his fellow, behold his owne countenance in the glaſſe, and then let him beare his anger firſt, which hath thus transformed and disfigured him.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, hee who hath placed the ſand a bound for the ſea, that intractible and foming Element, who hath taught the Vnicorne to abide by his crib; hee doeth nurture Beares, and teach young Lyons to ſeeke vnto him for their prey; Woolues, and Badgers, are his obedient ſlaues.</p>
               <p>Yea the poiſon of Aſpes, Scorpions, and Toades, are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered by his great hand, to the common good of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body; his hand hath alſo tempered the paſsion of anger, to the good of the leſſer body man-kinde.</p>
               <p>I hold not with the Stoickes, who hold a vacuitie of paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Chriſt our righteouſnes was angry, ſometimes when he lived vpon earth, as alſo he wanted not any other the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, griefe, ioy, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In heaven there ſhall bee perfect peace, and ioy without interruption; and I ſee there no cauſe of anger. As the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes therefore of the beaſts vnder the Law, were exempted from the ſacrifice: ſo the ſpleene and gall of our natures, which ſerue here onely to feed our male contented paſsions, ſhall be exempted, it may bee, or left at the bottome of the hill; when wee aſcend that holy Mount, which reacheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the cloudes, and the Citie which is the mother of vs all.</p>
               <p>But in the terrene condition of ours, ſo throughly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with euils, the onely true obiects of anger; God hath ſeated it among the other affections of the minde, as not onely vſefull, but neceſſary in this life; and it is that to the ſoule, which the Nerue is to the body, a whetſtone of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, a ſpurre to vertue, and honourable actions.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19643:10"/>
               <p> Among all the other parts therefore, before mentioned in angers deſcription, let vs take into a little further view, the obiect whereupon it is bent, and concerning which it is to be directed.</p>
               <p>The onely obiect of anger is evill, whether reall, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, but moſt truely reall; and therefore <hi>Ionah</hi> here was much miſtaken, in that he made God the obiect of his anger, who is goodneſſe it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Others have divided anger according to the obiects, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to anger inhumane, as to be ſavage againſt kinde and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; madde, as that of <hi>Balaams,</hi> to be angry with his Aſſe ſenſeleſſe; as that of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> to bee angry with the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Aethos,</hi> to be angry with the River Helleſpont.</p>
               <p>I affirme, that evill is the onely obiect of anger, and is in our ſelues or others.</p>
               <p>Firſt for our ſelues, for there is a time, when wee ought to be angry with our ſelues.</p>
               <p>An old man there was once heard chiding, hee was asked with whom? with a certaine old man quoth he, who weareth gray-haires, but wanteth vnderſtanding. And ſo <hi>Plato</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a time, went in haſt to beate his ſeruant, and taking the ſcourge of correction in his hand, hee ſtood ſtill for a good ſpace, with his hand lifted vp, and in the end ſpake thus; <hi>exigo paenas ab irato,</hi> I chaſtiſe quoth he, my owne anger.</p>
               <p>Thus anger rightly beſtowed againſt our ſelues, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doeth commend in the 7. Chap. the 2 Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as a noble branch of repentance, or godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. For the ſame, that yee ſorrowed after a godly ſorrow, ſaith hee, (among other fruites) what indignation or anger hath it wrought? Yea what revenge? What anger will you ſay? Why, be angry ſaith Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> againſt your ſinnes, the divell, lies, vanities, your ſelues.</p>
               <p>What revenge? Be revenged vpon your ſinnes, the divell lies, vanities, your ſelues.</p>
               <p>Oh, when will the edge of our anger, of our revenge bee turned this wayes! This is a noble anger, to be angry with what God is angry; a worthy revenge, when vertue doeth chaſtiſe vice. Behold ſaith the Apoſtle, hee ſpeakes it with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19643:11"/>an <hi>Ecce,</hi> the ſame that ye ſorrowed as ye ought, what anger? what revenge, &amp;c. This is a victory moſt acceptable vnto God, and ſhall be crowned of him, with a crowne of glory.</p>
               <p>There is a time alſo, wherein wee may be angry with our brethren, but with greater caution ought this to bee tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered.</p>
               <p>For we are but ſeldome angry with our ſelues; but often with our brethren; but a very little angry with our ſelues; very much with our brethren, making that to be but a mote in our owne eyes, which is a beame in our brothers.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle hath a very apt, and wholeſome admonition to this purpoſe, in the firſt verſe of his fourth Chapter to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> each word containing a ſecret argument to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent anger: Brethren, if a man be overtaken with a fault, yee which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch an one in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe, conſidering thy ſelfe, leaſt thou alſo bee tempted.</p>
               <p>More ſpecially, in our anger to others, obſerue wee theſe two, the manner, the meaſure: for the manner, walke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old rule well knowne, little practiſed; hate the offence, love the perſon.</p>
               <p>How can this bee? I anſwere, how is the father angry with his childe? Even ſo, that though hee chaſtiſe the fault, he loveth the childe; ſo be angry with thy brother, that yet thou be in charitie with him.</p>
               <p>This is an hard leſſon, may ſome ſay, both to hate, and love, at the ſame time: but in other matters of leſſe waight, thou knoweſt wiſely enough, how to diſtinguiſh.</p>
               <p>For if thou have a garment that is beſpotted, thou knoweſt how to take out the ſpot from thy garment, not to reiect the garment for the ſpot: even ſo take out the moth that is in thy brothers eye, but preſerue and doe not deſtroy the eye, becauſe of the mote in the eye.</p>
               <p>So for the meaſure of our anger, I ſhall not neede in many words to preſcribe.</p>
               <p>It was prohibited to the Iewes, in correction to their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that they ſhould not exceede the number of fortie ſtripes; wee being for the moſt part in caſes of priuate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19643:11"/>revenge culpable of that which was obiected againſt the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites by the Prophet <hi>Obed,</hi> in their dealing againſt their brethren of Iudah, vnder the raigne of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> viz. that they perſecuted them with a rage that reached vp vnto heaven.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour in the 5. of Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> doth mention three degrees (beſides actuall murder, which is to bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with death by mans law) of vnlawfull anger.</p>
               <p>The firſt in thought, he that is angry with his brother, the ſecond in geſture or ſigne, hee that ſaieth to his brother <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi> which word ſignifies anger, and in the ſpeech of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour doth forbid all ſignification of our anger to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, either in looke or countenance, or by any other ſigne or geſture.</p>
               <p>The third ſort of vnlawfull anger there mentioned, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by word, or tongue; hee that ſaith thou foole, or gives any other reproachfull prouoking termes, or ſpeeches to his brother.</p>
               <p>The whole text runnes thus, Whoſoever is angry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; but whoſoeuer ſhall ſay, Thou foole, ſhall be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of hell fire.</p>
               <p>Then beware of offending in the firſt kinde, being angry in thy ſecret thought againſt thy brethren, take heede more eſpecially, it be not manifeſted by ſome outward ſigne, take heede moſt of all theſe, it breake not out into intemperate language.</p>
               <p>If thou feare not the Iudgement, feare an aſſembly, or counſell; if you feare not the counſell, ſtand in awe and tremble at hell fire.</p>
               <p>But heere now a very neceſſary queſtion doth ariſe; If an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be ſo ſtrictly forbidden as we ſee; what courſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie is then left vnto vs in all iuſt provocations of wrath, and concerning the manifold iniuries, which are daily offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to our perſons, how are we to behave our ſelues?</p>
               <p>A queſtion truly well worthy to bee diſcuſſed, and the ſame very apt and pertinent to the Treatiſe of Anger.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I anſwere, that we ought at all times abſtaine from anger, even to our very thoughts, ſaving in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19643:12"/>manner as is before ſpoken to be angry with the ſinne, not with the perſon.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, we are not debarred the vſe of lawfull courſes, in the remedying of wrongs, and preventing further dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, when we are iuſtly thereunto provoked, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe maintaine peace.</p>
               <p>But wilt thou know wherein? tread not the path of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and goe not in the way which thy intemperate an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger would leade thee: But follow the counſell of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour; whoſe words in this cauſe are ſo plaine; I wonder any man ſhould miſtake, whoſe aduiſe is ſo whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, I wonder all men doe not more regard it. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. Theſe be his words, If thy brother ſhall treſpaſſe againſt thee, goe and tell him of his fault betweene thee and him alone, if hee ſhall heare thee, thou haſt gained thy brother; but if he will not heare thee, then take with thee one or two more; that in the mouth of two or three witneſſes, every word may be eſtabliſhed; and if hee ſhall neglect them, tell it vnto the Church, but if he neglect the Church let him bee vnto thee as an Heathen man or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</p>
               <p>Where you ſee, all meanes by Chriſtians lawfull to bee vſed, to be expreſſed by our Saviour; the firſt priuate, the ſecond more open, the third moſt publike; all friendly, but if all will not ſerue, he is no longer to be eſteemed as a friend, with whom we are to deale.</p>
               <p>The two firſt are well knowne, but how little vſed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right vſe of the laſt is vnknowne or moſt abuſed: By which laſt, the Church, I doe vnderſtand; ſuch as are deputed in the ſtead of Chriſt for well ordering cauſes, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſome the Church repreſentiue.</p>
               <p>For our Saviour here ſpeakes from the manner of the Iewes Common-wealth, who had Elders in every Citie, the firſt beginning whereof was from <hi>Iethro,</hi> whoſe office was to heare and iudge of controverſies, and end ſuits in law: Anſwerable whereto in our Common-wealth (comparable, I thinke I may boldly ſay to that of theirs, and inferiour at this day to no other, for matters of Policie and Church-government,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19643:12"/>if as truly executed) for Eccleſiaſticall matters, are the ſpiritualitie, and ſuch as ſtudy the Civill lawes: in matters temporall, the Magiſtrate, and they who ſtudie the Common lawes, for the maintenance of outward peace, and tranquillitie, in this our Church and Common-wealth. Let this be the Church then in this ſence: Tell the Church, (not a Presbyterie compacted of I know not who, as the Reformiſts of our time would) the Governours in this our Church and Kingdome, appointed for the outward preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of peace and tranquillitie.</p>
               <p>And this is the way, the order; every man ought to vſe in particular, to worke his peace and agreement with his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary.</p>
               <p>Not firſt to runne to the Church, to tell the Church, as the vſuall manner now adaies is; falling at firſt to ſuits in law, open contentious, branglings and ianglings in Courts Eccleſiaſticall and Temporall, whereof their is no end; God iuſtly puniſhing contentions minds, becauſe they love not peace, with diſſentions, all the daies of their lifes.</p>
               <p>But this is the courſe we ought to vſe, if we meane to be directed by Chriſt his aduiſe and counſell.</p>
               <p>Firſt, goe to thy brother, and admoniſh him of his fault betweene thy ſelfe and him alone in friendly manner. What hurt can come vnto thee by doing ſo? for if thou gaine him to a better minde, then bleſſed ſhalt thou be of the Lord, and he will alſo bleſſe God for thee, this is to love thine enemie according to the perfect rule of charitie.</p>
               <p>If he regard not this, then take with thee one or two more according to the rule in the ſecond place preſcribed; thou haſt caſt him before God, ſo before men alſo; if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he proove not bettered; thou thy ſelfe thus bridling thine anger, haſt freed thy owne ſoule from the danger of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Counſell, and haſt brought him within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of both, that God in due time may revenge as a Iudge, &amp; men may witneſſe his iuſtice againſt thy aduerſary.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, continuing ſtill obſtinate to bee thine enemie without a cauſe, thou mayeſt then complaine to the Church of him, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae;</hi> Tell the Church of him, bring him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19643:13"/>to the Bench, or to the Barre before the Iudge, whether Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall or Temporall; that he may bee openly convicted in Law, and then if ſtill hee remaine refractory, let him be to thee as an Heathen or Publican, as a man excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</p>
               <p>Thus it ought to be my brethren, this is the right order of proceeding; Peace be vpon them and vpon the Iſrael of God, peace ſhall be vpon them, and vpon the Iſrael of God, who walke according to this rule.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay, the caſe being farre otherwiſe? I will take vp my complaint with the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is farre from vs, neither doth iuſtice overtake vs, wee waight for light, but behold obſcuritie; for brightneſſe, but we walke in darkeneſſe.</p>
               <p>We roare all like Beares, and mourne like Doues; Citie and Countrey cry out for Iuſtice, Iuſtice; Citie nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey doe take the right courſe, proceeding in that order our Saviour hath left vs, therefore are many overthrowne in a rightfull cauſe.</p>
               <p>Hence ſprings that generall clamour againſt Lawyers, (which howſoever God will not overpaſſe, and a fearefull woe there is belonging to the vniuſt nouriſhers of debate; to thee alſo doe I ſay, whoſe office it is to determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, if thou hold them longer in ſuſpence, if thou perverteſt the cauſe in iudgement, howſoever God may vſe thee as an inſtrument, to vexe the contentious and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome ſpirits of ſome, yet this thy rapine and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall in the end ſinke thee lower into hell).</p>
               <p>Yet I am perſwaded many ſhould have more happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in their ſuits, if they did not begin in ſo rough manner at the firſt. But as I haue ſhewed; or if it ſucceede well enough with them for the preſent, yet it ſhall increaſe their iudgement with God, to a greater meaſure afterward.</p>
               <p>The men of this age, if they ſuſtaine the leaſt wrong, breath out nothing but law, law; whereas they ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the right vſe of the law is never ſeparated from charitie, and to fall to open pleadings, before priuate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, in Gods ſight is a plaine breach of the ſixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19643:13"/>whereby ſuch an one doth ſhew his hatred to his brother.</p>
               <p>Let vs vſe all courſes before we fall to Law-courſes, for this is the laſt meane which Chriſt hath left for the quieting and ordering of his Church, to goe laſtly (all other waies firſt tryed, to ſuch whom God hath ſet in publike office in his Church, which order becauſe many doe pervert, being carryed away, rather with a ſpirit of malice and rancour, then of vnitie and loue,) God doth ſuffer to winde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into many, and in inextricable Laberinths of trouble.</p>
               <p>And thus much for anger in generall, occaſioned from the text, rather then intended, and how to order and preſerve the ſame within convenient bounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="particular">
               <head>4. Particular.</head>
               <p>The queſtion in ſpeciall doth concerne <hi>Ionah's</hi> anger and the cauſe thereof according to theſe words, <hi>Ionah, Doeſt thou well to be angry for the Gourd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here firſt the manner of correction in this forme of ſpeech which the Lord vſeth, deſerveth to be noted. For a man would rather have looked for burning coales to have proceeded from his lippes; here is no more but thus, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bowe the heavens O Lord, and come downe, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Touch the mountaines and they ſhall ſmoake: caſt forth hightnings and ſcatter them, ſhoote out arrowes and deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>Let <hi>Peter</hi> be Iudge, and he will call for fire from heaven to conſume an whole Citie, much rather vpon one ſinfull man, that dareth to conteſt with the Lord of glory. What? ſhall the pot contend with the Potter, or the thing formed, ſay to the Former, Why haſt thou made me thus?</p>
               <p>Note the great clemencie of the Lord to <hi>Ionah</hi> herein, but not without application to our ſelues: For doth he not in as milde and louing manner deale with vs, ſending his Prophets riſing early and ſending them, in his name to deale with vs by exhortations, invitations, promiſes of loue, and proteſtations to receive vs if we will convert and turne vnto him.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19643:14"/>
               <p> We beſeech you by the tender mercies of God, ſaith Sait <hi>Paul;</hi> We intreate you as his Embaſſadours to be reconciled vnto God, when we are fallen out with him as <hi>Ionah</hi> heere. Heare what God himſelfe ſaith by his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo oft as we decline his precepts; Doe ye thus requite the Lord, O fooliſh people and vnwiſe? is not hee thy Father that hath bought thee? hath he not made thee, and eſtabliſhed thee? O <hi>Ephraim,</hi> what ſhall I doe vnto thee? O <hi>Iudah,</hi> what ſhall I doe vnto thee? my bowels are turned within me, my repentings are kindled within mee? waſh thee from thy ſinnes, O <hi>England,</hi> cleanſe thy ſelfe from thy pollutions, O <hi>London,</hi> when will it be?</p>
               <p>Is not our God a conſuming fire? are not the ſinners in Sion afraid of him? who ſhall dwell with everlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings?</p>
               <p>When the offer of mercy will not ſerue, he ſpeakes in the perſon of revenge and fury (for what are we but bryers and thornes to that conſuming flame?) and who would, ſaith he, ſet the bryers and thornes againſt mee in the day of battell? I would goe thorow them; I would burne them together. Behold I am preſſed vnder you, ſaith he by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Prophet, as a cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaves. Therefore alſo he ſaith in another place, ah, I will eaſe me of mine aduerſaries, and avenge me of mine enemies.</p>
               <p>And againe, if I whet my glittering ſword, and my hand take hold on iudgement; I will render vengeance to mine enemies and repay them that hate me.</p>
               <p>But yet he ſpeakes peace vnto his people, mercy and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe all the day long: why will yee die, O yee houſe of Iſrael? I deſire not the death of a ſinner; why art thou all ſo angry, O <hi>Ionah,</hi> I have given thee no iuſt cauſe, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry thus againſt thy Maker?</hi> be not ſo peruerſe in thy fury, but iudge righteous iudgement.</p>
               <p>The ſame I ſay to thee, and every one elſe in particular (for the Lords words are both particularly vniuerſall and vniverſally particular) that which at firſt was delivered to one Tribe, is applyable to all Tribes and kindreds of the earth, and the word preached to an whole Citie, is brought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19643:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>home to ſome few private conſciences, and is to be brought home to thine.</p>
               <p>Propound this that hath beene ſaid, as thine owne cauſe, and admiring not ſo much the Lords patience towards <hi>Ionah,</hi> as towards thy ſelfe; aske theſe queſtions of thine owne ſoule.</p>
               <p>Whether thou doe well to deferre thy repentance, and turning vnto God ſo long, whether thou doe well at any time to be angry with thy God, or with thy brother, ſay oftentimes to thy ſelfe in thy paſsion and diſtemper of minde, doe I well to be thus impatient, thus fretfull, doe I well to be thus vnthankefull to my God, to provoke him, to grieve his holy Spirit?</p>
               <p>Is it better for mee to inioy God as my Father, or as a Iudge, a gracious Redeemer; or terrible revenger? to have my part in his bleſſed promiſes, by liſtening vnto his loving admonitions, or in thoſe fearefull comminations before mentioned by continuing obſtinate?</p>
               <p>An admirable clemencie was it in the Lord, in ſuch faire tearmes, to treate with <hi>Ionah</hi> his ſervant, his creature; but far greater his loue vnder this forme of reaſoning, to make <hi>Ionah</hi> his owne Iudge in the cauſe; by this meanes to reduce him to a more ſober minde, when as he ſaith to this effect; if thou thinke that thou art hardly dealt withall <hi>Ionah</hi> at my hand, and that I the Lord am no equall Iudge in thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, I referre the cauſe to thine owne cenſure, lay aſide wrath, and ſpeake out of a more ſerious conſideration, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou doe well to be angry, <hi>Angry with mee about the Gourd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus if we were wiſe, to take the whole benefite of this example, we ſhould not only admire his clemencie, but alſo avoide his iudgements, and procure his fauour, we being made our owne Iudge as before, for if we would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not be iudged of the Lord, as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Corinthians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="cause">
               <head>The cauſe of <hi>Ionahs</hi> anger.</head>
               <p>It is expreſſed here in the text, the Gourd; <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry for the Gourd?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19643:15"/>
               <p> A ſilly matter to be angry for, yea to be angry with the great God in this regard only: But this vndoubtedly is not the only cauſe, but many things beſides, as vpon this ground, doe offer themſelues to the minde of <hi>Ionah,</hi> as the ſparke to the tinder, the match to the ſparke.</p>
               <p>Yea indeede, <hi>Ionah</hi> was as an hotte oven damm'd vp, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vent, for he was angry before, as may appeare from the ſecond verſe of this Chapter, he was not well pleaſed at firſt, now this Gourd doth both increaſe the heate and makes paſſage.</p>
               <p>Let vs put vpon vs the perſon of <hi>Ionah,</hi> and reaſon the whole matter, ſo farre as by circumſtance we are able to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in his behalfe.</p>
               <p>And firſt looke wee vnto the office of <hi>Ionah;</hi> He was a Prophet, a name of honour, ſo of great labour and mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation; pride lookes contemptuouſly at the function, envy weaves many ſubtill diſgraces, to bring downe the honour of it, all the armies of vices doe bandon againſt it, and he who hath vndertaken this office, muſt ſhow himſelfe a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt enemie to the times iniquities, <hi>Ionah</hi> was a Prophet.</p>
               <p>So he was a Prophet to thoſe revolting Tribes of Iſrael, of whoſe incorrigibleneſſe all the other Prophets have complained.</p>
               <p>And now after that he hath wearied and ſpent himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe, hee is ſent vnto a ſtout-hearted people the Ninevites.</p>
               <p>And what hope of better fruit and ſucceſſe of his labours amongſt an vnbeleeving nation? Or if perchance they proove beleeving and repent, then is the credite of his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage called in queſtion; this made him at the firſt to flye to Tarſhiſh.</p>
               <p>Now after ſo many iournyings by land, and toſsings by ſea, he takes vp his lodging in the belly of a Whale-fiſh.</p>
               <p>He is out of that naſtie place deliuered, as out of the mouth of hell, and now is commanded the ſecond time for Nineveh.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Ionah</hi> muſt put on a firme reſolution, either to be ſlaine, or elſe derided, if the feare of God be not in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19643:15"/>place, then <hi>Ionah</hi> hath ſpoken words, the land is not able to beare; Flee oh thou ſeer and eſcape for thy life.</p>
               <p>Or if the feare of God doe worke in their hearts to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendment; then hearke to <hi>Ionah,</hi> I pray thee O Lord, ſaith he, was not this my ſaying, when I was yet in my owne countrey? therefore I fled before vnto Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiſh, for I knew that thou art a gracious God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now after all theſe labours, after all theſe dolours, ſome poore refreſhment ſprings vp to <hi>Ionah,</hi> a Gourd from the ground to comfort <hi>Ionah's</hi> head in this great diſquiet, and paine of <hi>Ionah's</hi> heart.</p>
               <p>The Lord prepared a Gourd to overſhadow <hi>Ionah's</hi> head, and therewith he was content to forget his preſent myſerie (for now thinkes he, the Lord begins to remember my affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,) and flatters himſelfe from this conceit, that the Lord will proceede to adde further conſolation, and herein <hi>Ionah</hi> was exceeding glad of the Gourd.</p>
               <p>But behold, on the ſuddaine all his mirth is marr'd; <hi>Ionah's</hi> reioycing laſteth but for a night; <hi>Ionah</hi> awakes in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and finds the Gourd quite decayed, and all his pleaſure therewith vaniſhed.</p>
               <p>Thus am I croſſed ſaith <hi>Ionah</hi> every way thus am I moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, thus deceiued; thus am I altogether, and on all ſides vexed.</p>
               <p>And it came to paſſe ſaith the text, when the Sun did ariſe, that God prepared a vehement Eaſt-winde, and the Sunne beate vpon the head of <hi>Ionah,</hi> that he fainted, and wiſhed in himſelfe to dye and ſaid: It is better for me to dye then to live.</p>
               <p>Now ſaith God to <hi>Ionah</hi> (thus many reaſons no doubt, and many more in his thoughts being amaſſed together) <hi>Ionah, Doeſt thou well to be angry, or art thou exceeding angry?</hi> yea ſaith <hi>Ionah,</hi> I am exceeding angry, <hi>yea I doe well to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry to the death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee the cauſe or rather cauſes of <hi>Ionah's</hi> anger? (to content my ſelfe with one onely obſervation, let vs learne from hence, thus much for our inſtruction.</p>
               <p>Namely, from the orderly, or rather diſorderly working
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19643:16"/>of <hi>Ionah's</hi> paſsions (the preſent being vſed as an inſtrument to rake vp the embers of all his former diſcontents) how to carry our ſelves in tryals of this nature, to prevent or defeate Satans wiles and policies herein.</p>
               <p>For we have to deale with a ſubtill adverſary, who workes vpon the advantage of our diſtempered weakeneſſe.</p>
               <p>He perceived <hi>Ionah</hi> much out of pacience before, and now he doth vſe the helpes of the Gourd, to worke him quite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelfe: ſo if he at any time finde vs to have delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp the hold of reaſon, or to be vpon the tyde of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent paſsions, he plyes the advantage with diligence, and though we ſayle too faſt of our ſelves, he will not ſticke to adde both winde and water to our Ships.</p>
               <p>Hee ſaith to the angry man, beſides the preſent occaſion of his anger, remember wrongs of old done vnto thee; hee hath treſpaſſed againſt me ſeuen times; yea, though his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come and humble himſelfe in preſence, hee will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of the counſell of our Saviour, the power of temptation doeth prevaile more ſtrongly, and fleſh and blood cannot withſtand.</p>
               <p>To the furious man, hee likewiſe ſaith ſtrike him; the ſecond time, ſtrike him to the ground; the third time, ſtrike him ſure; for revenge is a ſweete thing, there is glory in the killing of a man, and to put on the girdle of blood vpon thy loynes, it is ſure, an act of generoſitie.</p>
               <p>To the adulterer, when he perceives him inclining to that ſinne, hee inſinuates himſelfe by many goodly reaſons, and ſaith; the good man is gone from home, the darkeneſſe ſhall cover thee, none eye ſhall ſee thee; ſtolne waters are ſweete, and bread of deceite eaten in ſecret is pleaſant; but hee telles him not, that his mouth in the end ſhall bee filled with gravell.</p>
               <p>To the woman, and laſcivious perſon, hee preſenteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the obiect; which for the preſent pleaſeth the eye, the pleaſure of actuall inioying; ſhee hath coſtly and gay hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whom I make the miſtris of my delight.</p>
               <p>I have decked my bed, ſpeaketh ſhee, with coverings of Tapiſtrie, with carved workes, with fine linnen of Egypt;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19643:16"/>I have perfumed my bed with Myrrhe, Aloes, and Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
               <p>Yea, ſhee is a religious Strumpet too, this day have I paid my vowes; ſhe goes to Church, but more to intangle ſimple ones in her eye-lids, then to heare a Sermon: Oh, ſhee rides in her Coach like a Queene of beautie. Thus the wanton is taken, with theſe and many the like; with ditties, and daunces, with roſe-beds, and garlands, and crownes of roſes.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo doeth our tempter deale with vs, by temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the left hand.</p>
               <p>If hee perceive our mindes doubtfull, and wavering from God-ward; he calles to our remembrance, how many good deedes of ours have paſſed vnregarded; how oft wee have prayed, and have returned without ſucceſſe in our prayers, that it is in vaine to ſerue God; and thus hee tempts to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie.</p>
               <p>When hee ſees vs troubled with ſome preſent miſhap, hee calles to minde all the croſſes wee have borne heretofore; that God doeth ſtill loade vs with dayly aflictions, without reliefe, without releaſe, and thus he tempts vs to impacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; even as he deales with <hi>Ionah</hi> here, finding him troubled about the gourd, he awakens alſo his former diſcontents, the moleſtations of his calling, his travels by Land, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts by Sea; and makes him in the end to fall out, and be at plaine difference with God.</p>
               <p>Wherefore happie is that man, that can prudently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, and diſcerning hold out the ſhield of Faith, to quench all the fierie darts of Satan.</p>
               <p>The ayre is not oftner viſited with windes of all quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, gentle, or rough, bringing, or chaſing away raine, blaſting or bleſsing the fruits of the earth; then is the minde of man with the contrary blaſts or breathings from two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſpirits from above, and from below.</p>
               <p>Happie is that man, who is wiſe to diſcerne the times and ſeaſons of ſpirituall moovings, who (though he know not whence the winde ariſeth) doth open the windowes and doores of his ſoules garden, to let in thoſe heavenly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19643:17"/>and breathings from above the ſpices of his garden ſhall flow out, or if he ſet to ſea, he ſhall arrive vnto plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant harbour.</p>
               <p>But woefull is his miſtake, who hoyſeth ſayle when the Diuell keepes his quarter, whether muſt he be carryed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe into the vnfortunate Iſlands, vnleſſe before his tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings rent, his Ship doe ſplit, and his hopes be ſinked into the bottome of the Ocean.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I conclude againe, obſerve the times, and the firſt beginnings, if they appeare inticements, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, temptations vnto evill vnto ſinne.</p>
               <p>For if we be once vpon the tyde of our head-ſtrong affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, a great meaſure of grace is required to ſtay vs, and if once we begin to tumble, the waight of our natures will not eaſily be letted from the bottome of the hill, and we be mainely bruiſed or everlaſtingly periſhed.</p>
               <p>And thus much for the cauſe of <hi>Ionahs</hi> anger which is not only the Gourd, though it only by the Lord be mentioned in the text.</p>
               <p>It was for this end, not to make <hi>Ionah</hi> more impacient but an argument vſed by the Lord to confute his former great impaciencie as in the next words, the concluſion of the booke is made plaine. And thus farre on the Lords part: the firſt generall part have we proceeded; The next maine part now in order followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Anſwere of <hi>Ionah.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And he ſaid, yea, I doe well to be angry even vnto death.</p>
               <p>I ſhould little have expected ſuch an anſwere from the mouth of <hi>Ionah,</hi> eſpecially having beene ſo mainely ſchoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but a little before. What? to the third degree? yea, <hi>I am angry; I doe well to be angry; I doe well to be angry vnto death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> is now got out of the deepe vpon the firme land, he no longer feares the wiudes, the ratling tempeſt, the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nor the Whale. But God is the ſame God both by ſea and land; thinke on this <hi>Ionah,</hi> that hee is not as thou ſuppoſeſt.</p>
               <p>But as hee hath the Leviathan and Whirle-poole of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19643:17"/>deepe, ſo hath his hand formed the crooked Serpent of the land, yea he can make theſe contemptible vermine, with whom thou daily converſeſt to bite thee; as he made <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> Aſſe to reproove the madneſſe of the Prophet.</p>
               <p>Whom doeſt thou provoke <hi>Ionah?</hi> art thou able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend? Cloath now thy ſelfe with thunder, and ſcatter light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings over the face of the earth.</p>
               <p>Gird vp thy loynes like a man and ſpeake, for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe demandeth of thee; where waſt thou when I laide the foundations of the earth, when I laide the meaſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſtretcht the line vpon it, when I laide the corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, the morning Starres then ſang together, and all the ſonnes of God ſhouted for ioy?</p>
               <p>Who ſhut vp the ſea with doores, and made the cloude a garment, and thicke darkneſſe a ſwadling band for it?</p>
               <p>Mightie <hi>Ionah,</hi> powerfull <hi>Ionah,</hi> dreadfull <hi>Jonah,</hi> lift vp now thy voyce to the cloudes, and cauſe abundance of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to couer thee; haſt thou an arme like God? or canſt thou thunder with a voyce like him? Decke thy ſelfe now with Maieſtie and excellencie, caſt abroad the rage of thy wrath, behold every one that is high and abaſe him.</p>
               <p>Fretfull <hi>Ionah,</hi> angry <hi>Ionah,</hi> pettiſh <hi>Ionah,</hi> fooliſh <hi>Ionah,</hi> whom doeſt thou provoke, ſtand now to thy cauſe, and conſider wiſely what argument thou takeſt in hand, and doe not darken counſell by words without knowledge, which was <hi>Iobs</hi> fault before thee, and ought of thee more adviſedly to be confidered, now that it comes to be thy caſe.</p>
               <p>But it fares with <hi>Ionah,</hi> as with a man borne downe with a violent ſtreame, the law of his members is at this time ſo powerfull in him, that there is little and no appearance of the life of grace. Conſider the degrees, and firſt:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="affirmation">
               <head>His affirmation.</head>
               <p>Yea, ſaith <hi>Ionah;</hi> he doth not conceale his inward heate, as if it would burne his heart out if he ſhould.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> had but little time to confider betweene the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Lord put vnto him, and the anſwere by him to be made, and the fury of his inward paſsions, the while raging;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19643:18"/>no great maruaile if ſome diſtempered heate appeare, and he anſwere out of reaſon.</p>
               <p>A man who is in a tempeſt at the ſea, hath not (while the tempeſt laſteth) the government either of himſelfe, or any thing about him: and thus is <hi>Ionah</hi> the ſecond time loſed in the ſurging ſeas of his owne paſsions.</p>
               <p>The which may teach vs therefore to doe nothing, while the heate of the paſsion laſteth, but vpon premeditated tearmes.</p>
               <p>For what? when it flyes in the face of God, what will not anger dare to doe? <hi>Occiderem te,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>ni iratus ſim,</hi> I would kill thee, but that I am angry with thee; whereas we know not how to fight in other temper, and never ſtrike but in our anger, like the Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the ſecond, who beeing deprived of his noſe by <hi>Leoncius</hi> his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, vpon every remembrance of that iniury, cauſed ſome friend or other of that Emperour to looſe a noſe or be ſlaine.</p>
               <p>But I liſt not to ſtand vpon this, ſince <hi>Ionah</hi> contents not himſelfe with one poore word, yea, nor with a ſimple ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, but proceeds to a iuſtification, a deepe aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his anger according to the diviſion before remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</p>
               <p>Yet truly thus farre can I not chooſe but take notice, that albeit this very one word, ought not once to have beene conceived in the breaſt of <hi>Ionah,</hi> yet more tolerable had bin his fault, if here he had reſted and ſuppreſs't all further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of his vnguided ſpirit.</p>
               <p>And therefore here (by way of paſſage vnto the next point) learne we that advice of <hi>Salomon,</hi> Chap. 30. If thou have done fooliſhly in lifting vp thy ſelfe, or if thou have thought evill, lay thine hand vpon thy mouth, and ſtoppe thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger before it proceede too farre.</p>
               <p>For as followeth in the ſame place, the much churning of milke, changeth it into an other nature, and the wringing of the noſe bringeth forth blood, ſo the forcing of wrath in the end commonly bringeth forth ſtrife, ſtrife blood-ſhed, blood-ſhed death oftentimes and perill of eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19643:18"/>to the name, perſon, or poſteritie of ſuch, who give themſelves over to the government of this fury.</p>
               <p>A cholericke man for this cauſe, or he that gives eaſie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to his anger, is not vnfitly compared to a man dwelling in a thatcht houſe, who being therein rich in the morning, ſets it all on a light fire before the evening; for Anger ſlaies the fooliſh, ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore once againe, quench it while it is a ſparke, which is not ſo eaſily done, after it hath got head; ſhut the flood-gates before the ſtreame grow too violent, and beare downe all before it.</p>
               <p>But what ſhould <hi>Ionah</hi> doe? muſt he not anſwere to the Lords queſtion? for the Lord doth aske him, <hi>if he doe well to be angry,</hi> and ſince that ſo he is, and ſo thinketh, as good ſpeake it as diſſemble.</p>
               <p>I finde the ſame queſtion before in the fourth verſe, put vnto <hi>Ionah</hi> by the Lord in the ſame manner, yet I meete not there with any word of <hi>Ionah</hi> by way of anſwere expreſt.</p>
               <p>Belike (as there he was ſullen and would not) ſo now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorowly heated with this fire, he cannot refraine any longer, but muſt out with it.</p>
               <p>He continued (as ſhould ſeeme) from that time to this, ſaving only a little <hi>Interim</hi> for one nights reſt, like vnto a greene peece of wood or chubbed blocke which lies over a few coales ſmoaking and ſmouldring; but now the moyſture being well ſuckt out, he breakes into a light flame, and ſpits and ſpartles fire againſt the Lord: note his manner in the ſecond ſpecialtie of his ſpeech.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="justification">
               <head>2. His peremptory Aſſeveration or Iuſtification.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I doe well to be angry.</hi> It was a milde ſaying of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour to one of his ſouldiers deſirous to be diſmiſſed his armie, but wanting a iuſt and honeſt excuſe to his friends at his returne home, ſay, ſaith the Emperour, that I have angried thee.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay to thee <hi>Ionah,</hi> who art angry not in ſhew, but in deede? who vndertakeſt to iuſtifie thy anger, and that not againſt an earthly Emperour, but againſt ſuch a great King, who caſteth out the glory of all earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19643:19"/>and Empires like the clay in the ſtreets?</p>
               <p>I know not ſurely well what to ſay to it: yet this I am ſure of, that mightie Cedars I ſee ſometimes to be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſhaken, that he who thinketh hee ſtandeth may looke better to his ſtanding.</p>
               <p>Wee have a pregnant example in <hi>Ionah</hi> here, a choſen man in Iſrael, and one of the worthies of God.</p>
               <p>I'le ſpeake no more then what I know: yet my knowledge herein I muſt confeſſe is ledde into a wonderment, when I conſider, as I finde it.</p>
               <p>Now, in that heavenly <hi>Chorus,</hi> next vnto thoſe glorious Cherubins and Seraphins who continually doe cry, Holy, Holy, Holy, we ſhall doe well to ranke the glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Apoſtles; and after them the goodly fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Prophets; and next to theſe, the noble Armies of the Martyrs.</p>
               <p>And why ſay I this thing? that you may alſo wonder to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with mee, when I have ſhowne vnto you, what I have obſerved from the great weakeneſſe in this kinde of the holy and moſt honoured Prophets of God.</p>
               <p>When you ſhall behold, ſuch who have commanded the waters, had power over fire, who have travelled the ſea, rode in the ayre, ſubdued kingdomes, wrought righteouſneſſe, beene renowned in their times, and left the glory of their names vnto poſterities; theſe I ſay to have beene conquering and prevailing over all outward force, yet of their owne vnruly appetites to be brought into ſubiection, or of their inward paſsions to have beene mainely foyled.</p>
               <p>Yea, I have not yet diſcovered the whole truth: for I muſt needs ſay that I have found none, as comparable to the Prophets in the aboveſaid reſpects: ſo like them none, to have beene tranſported in the like meaſure, or carryed with ſuch diſordered violence as theſe, and thoſe, who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the beſt teſtimonies from, and beene graced with the greateſt honour from his hand.</p>
               <p>Let vs caſt our eyes from <hi>Ionah,</hi> the moſt cleere example of all others vpon <hi>Moſes</hi> that man of God, and Prophet likewiſe, greater then whom none did riſe till Chriſt came.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19643:19"/>
               <p> He is reported for the meekeſt man vpon the earth then living, yet cannot be excuſed for ſpeaking vnadviſedly with his lippes at the waters of Meribah. Or if we could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to paſſe by this, what ſhall we ſay to that which fell out a little after the conſumption at Taberah?</p>
               <p>What great reaſon had <hi>Moſes</hi> there to grow weary of his charge? ſo weary, that he deſired to dye? ſo deſirous of death that he prayeth the Lord to ſlay him? as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the 11. Chapter of <hi>Numbers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is this the meeke man ſpoken of? yea, let him be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>ſecundum partem ſaniorem,</hi> ſo that yet wee ſuffer not <hi>Ionah</hi> to want a companion in his impaciencie, and my text receive confirmation from his example in like manner.</p>
               <p>Come we to <hi>Eliah,</hi> one that rode vp to heaven in a fierie Chariot, called by a Father a Waggoner in the ayre, a man ordained for reproofes, ſaith <hi>Syrach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet a man ſubiect to the ſame paſsions with others, and not voyde of reproofe himſelfe.</p>
               <p>It proceeded from the heate of his ſpirit, when he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that miſtake, as if there were none righteous but hee alone.</p>
               <p>But whereas he ſaith, O Lord, take away my life, he ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathiſeth directly with the words of <hi>Ionah</hi> before my text, who wiſhed in himſelfe to dye, and ſaid it is better for me to dye then live.</p>
               <p>And however, I cannot bee bold to ſay, that he would have returned the ſame anſwere with this of <hi>Ionah</hi> in the defence of his anger; yet ſure God might well at that time have put the ſame queſtion to him which is to <hi>Ionah; Doeſt thou well to be angry</hi> Eliah?</p>
               <p>I neede not to ſay much of <hi>Iob;</hi> nor doe I finde him ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked among the Prophets, yet ſure he is well worthy to bee honoured with the title.</p>
               <p>You have heard of the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iames,</hi> tis true, and of his great impatience too; who knowes not that, who is but meanely converſt in his ſtory; or the ſubſtance of reaſoning by his owne hand left in writing?</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19643:20"/>
               <p> Now come we to <hi>Ieremy,</hi> of whom, and to whom, I finde the Lord himſelfe thus ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>See, ſaith he, I have this day ſet thee over the nations, and over the kingdomes; to roote out and to pull downe, and to deſtroy and to throw downe, to build and to plant.</p>
               <p>But how much griefe and vexation this coſt him, you may behold. In the fifteenth Chapter, I heare him pleading thus, woe is mee, my mother, that thou haſt borne mee; a man of ſtrife, and a man of contention to the whole earth.</p>
               <p>In the twentieth Chap. thus, O Lord thou haſt deceived mee, and I was deceived; thou art ſtronger then I, and haſt prevailed; I am in deriſion daily, every one mocketh mee.</p>
               <p>Who ſaith that <hi>Ieremy</hi> had not iuſt cauſe to be angry? ſure, vnleſſe himſelfe had thought and beene perſwaded ſo, hee would never have broken out into theſe tearmes of heate and diſpleaſure againſt the Almighty.</p>
               <p>But towards the end of the ſame Chapter he growes horne-madde, and then hee falles to curſing: <hi>Iobs</hi> fit hath taken him, and thus he takes on, Curſed be the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was borne, ſaith he, let not the day wherein my mother bare mee be bleſſed; Curſed be the man who brought ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to my father, ſaying, a man-childe is borne vnto thee, making him very glad. And let that man bee as the Cities which God overthrew and repented not, and let him heare the cry in the morning, and the ſhouting at noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyde.</p>
               <p>And why <hi>Ieremy?</hi> and why? becauſe hee ſlew mee not from the wombe, ſaith he, or that my mother might have bin my grave, and her wombe to be alwaies great with me.</p>
               <p>Behold, a man even drunke with ſorrow; and thus hee reeles, and thus he ſtaggers, yet; an holy Prophet, a man ſanctified from the wombe.</p>
               <p>Take but one example more, and in a word; let <hi>Ezechiel</hi> be the man propheſying at the ſame time, and perplexed with the like vexations in his calling.</p>
               <p>He was moſt vnwilling to goe amongſt them of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie, howbeit, when needs he muſt, in this manner doth he expreſſe it.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19643:20"/>
               <p> The ſpirit lifted mee vp and tooke mee away, and I went in bitterneſſe, in the heate of my ſpirit or hot anger, but the hand of the Lord was ſtrong vpon me, Chapter 3.</p>
               <p>What now then ſhall we ſay to theſe things? ſince ſuch ſturdy oakes, <hi>Ionah, Ieremy, Iob, Eliah, Moſes,</hi> by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent blaſts of temptations are laide flat vpon the ground, what ſhall we ſay to theſe things?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, as before I ſaide, againe I ſay, let him that thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth he ſtands, take heede leaſt he fall.</p>
               <p>If it were ſo, that wee could command the winds from blowing, or beate downe the foming ſea: if we could reſtraine the bottles of heaven or repeale the crackes of thunder, then happily we might ſquare out the limits and appoint the meaſure of our moſt wiſhed peacefulneſſe, and drinke downe pleaſures as Leuia than the river Iordan.</p>
               <p>But when I heare the groanes of dying men, doe ſee the gaſpings (as it were) of many after breath, when I heare the horrible rage and ruſhing of the billowes, mightie flawes renting downe the tackling.</p>
               <p>When ſtrong men fall downe wounded the valiant ones cry bitterly, and the ſhield of the mightie be broken, alas for me then thinke I; how ſhall I bee able to ſtand in the day of battell?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> was not well adviſed when he ſaid in his poſteritie, I ſhall never bee mooved; thou Lord of thy favour hadſt made my hill ſo ſtrong. What followes vpon the ſame? thou diddeſt hide thy face and I was troubled.</p>
               <p>The place is remarkable concerning <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Kings of Iudah, where it is ſaid that in ſuch a buſineſſe, the Lord left him to try him, that he might know all that was in his heart.</p>
               <p>Alas; what vertue is in vs, and what power, to vanquiſh evill, is all from heaven, whoſe influence if it deſcend not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our fraile ſoules, wee preſently ſend forth cryes as from the depth of hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> left vnto himſelfe in Paradiſe fell, ſo did <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> ſo did <hi>Salomon</hi> the moſt glorious King that ever ſwayed a ſcepter.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19643:21"/>
               <p> And hence proceede even all thoſe bitter words of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt Saints that ever lived, to ſhew that their holyneſſe was not inherent properly in their owne perſons, for which cauſe the moſt ſanctifyed have ever retained the moſt ſober and humble conceits, in themſelves, of themſelves.</p>
               <p>And therefore away with all proud and ſwelling thoughts of the fleſh; and againe, I ſay let him that thus thinketh he ſtands, take heede, leaſt he fall.</p>
               <p>Secondly. So againe in the ſecond place to comfort weake ones in their manifold ſlippes and falles, this doctrine may not vnfitly be applyed.</p>
               <p>For why? I am not a <hi>Moſes,</hi> I am not an <hi>Eliah,</hi> a <hi>Iob,</hi> a <hi>Ionah,</hi> or a <hi>Ieremy;</hi> a meaner portion of grace ſhall content mee: Howbeit, by the grace of God I am that I am, and without the grace of God aſsiſting, the perfecteſt that ever were among the ſonnes of men (Chriſt only excepted) had not power of themſelves one houre to ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>In this then let mee cheere vp my heart, that if I fall into drunkenneſſe I have a <hi>Noah,</hi> to raiſe me when I am truly grieved; if into adultery I haue a <hi>David</hi> to ſupport mee, when my heart is truly affected with his penitentiall <hi>Pſalme;</hi> if into pride of heart, I have an <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to reſtore mee when the ſame heart is with godly ſorrow truly humbled.</p>
               <p>If I fall into plaine impaciencie, murmure and repining, I have a <hi>Moſes,</hi> a <hi>Iob,</hi> a <hi>Ieremy,</hi> a <hi>Ionah</hi> to direct mee, when vnto a more ſober and ſetled ſpirit with them I am returned.</p>
               <p>Let this vſe be made of the Saints faylings to comfort vs in our infirmities, not to animate vs in any wilfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties. Children they are not of God, but of Belial who doe this latter.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In the third place, ſince it is a Prophet that here complaineth, and we have obſerved the like complaints of ſundry the Prophets in the examination of this doctrine more then of any other kinds and profeſsions of men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               <p>Let the Prophets and Miniſters of God from hence learne ſomewhat to their inſtruction, at leaſt-wiſe a right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the calling and buſineſſe they take in hand.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19643:21"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Qui deſiderat Epiſcopatum, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, he that deſires the office of Biſhop or of ſome inferiour Paſtor and Teacher in the Church, he deſires a good worke.</p>
               <p>But now worke hath painfulneſſe, and this by few, I am ſure, is deſired; and if the calling may bee honourable, yet ſure, it is not eaſefull; Curſed is that man, eſpecially in this high and holy function, that divideth what God hath ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, honour and labour, or that ioyneth what God hath ſeparated, eaſe and honour.</p>
               <p>The Angels of God the higher in nature, the more quicke and diligent are they in their ſervice to God and to his Church, and the Prophets of God are called Angels, and the Angels Miniſters, and fellow-ſervants with them.</p>
               <p>Hee that ſhall with <hi>Atlas</hi> vnder-proppe the heavens, or with <hi>David</hi> (who was a Prophet) beare vp the pillars of the earth, no marveile if he groane ſometimes.</p>
               <p>And thinke not, that it was not for nothing, that <hi>Ionah</hi> here was thus beſides himſelfe; and ſo iudge of the former complaints of thoſe good Prophets mentioned, that they did proceede from the grievous preſſures and waight of thoſe burdens, which in the waightie charge of their callings they have ſuſtained.</p>
               <p>The names wherewith I finde the calling named, may partly inſtruct vs herein.</p>
               <p>Seers are they called, and o how long wilt thou cauſe mee to behold or ſee grievance, ſaith one of them? <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Shepheards they are called, and well may ſay with <hi>Iacob,</hi> Thus was it with mee in the day time, the heate conſumed mee, and the froſt by night, and my ſleepe departed from mine eyes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.</p>
               <p>Are they not alſo called Watch-men? and to them the voyce calleth, Watch-man what of the night? Watch-man what of the night? A Lyon my Lord, a Lyon; the roaring Lyon that goes about ſeeking whom hee may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure; Watch yee, ſtand yee faſt, quit your ſelves like men: I ſtand, I ſtand continually vpon the Watch-tower ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in the day time, and I am ſet in my Ward whole nights: &amp; you know to what end, to fore-ſee dangers.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19643:22"/>
               <p> Laſtly, they are called Fiſhers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. and here they muſt reſolve to grapple with many an hideous ſtorme. If <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew</hi> will follow Chriſt, they ſhall catch ſoules; but withall muſt looke to finde a ſea of trouble of it, when once they have launched out into the deepe.</p>
               <p>O that this were conſidered of at Naioth in Ramah, and in the Schooles of the Prophets!</p>
               <p>The Lacedaemonians had their <hi>Palaſtram</hi> or place of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe for the youth, that afterwards they might make choice of tryed ſouldiers againſt the times of needfull warre.</p>
               <p>What are thoſe houſes before named in the right intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but improovements vnto noble fortitude? that with the Prieſts of God, who ſounded the trumpets of old, the Prieſts of theſe dayes may proove incouragers to the Lords people, in the Lords battels againſt ſinne and wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diogenes</hi> vpon a time comming into the tent of <hi>Philip</hi> King of Macedon, was askt by him, if he came as a ſpye? yea quoth he, for I come to ſpye out thy folly and madneſſe, who being not conſtrained by any neceſsitie; doeſt ſet as it were vpon the dicing board both thy life and kingdome.</p>
               <p>Are not we according to the beſt acception, in as high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as ever was the Macedonian <hi>Philip?</hi> doth not the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of our office draw with it as great danger as his folly?</p>
               <p>How is it then that we, who ſhould bee leaders to the Lords people have cloathed our ſelves with the faſhions and humours of the times? in ſtead of the compleate Armour commended by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> have put on the ſword of infidelitie, the girdle of licentiouſneſſe, the breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of vnrighteouſneſſe, the ſhield of infidelitie?</p>
               <p>Whooredome and wine, and new wine, take away the heart, was the complaint of old.</p>
               <p>We have not leſſoned but added to the account, chambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and wantonneſſe, Tobacco too and drunkenneſſe are the ſins of theſe dayes, and which is worſt of all (I would not ſpeake it) the Prophets doe eate vp the ſins of the people.</p>
               <p>O that my head were a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſinnes of the Prophets?</p>
               <p>For the leaders of my people cauſe them to erre, ſaith
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19643:22"/>the Lord, leading them into blinde pathes and crooked waies, and they ſhall ſtumble and fall together, and none ſhall raiſe them vp, ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>The caſe indeede muſt needs proove deſperate, when they who ſhould ſupport doe ſtand in neede of ſupportation, and they who ſhould be raiſers vnto others, are themſelves down.</p>
               <p>Awake for ſhame, oh yee of the ſtocke and ſtemme of Levi, and let <hi>Aarons</hi> rod flouriſh in your hands, or elſe reſolve to burne eternally: Breake forth into thunder, o yee ſonnes of thunder, and let the trumpet yet ſound louder.</p>
               <p>Are not we the men who are now, even now to prepare a people againſt our Maſters ſecond comming? and is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Eliah</hi> thinke you ſufficient for vs? now is the time to be zealous, or never, or never.</p>
               <p>O let the people of God, pray for the Prieſts of God, O let the Prieſts of God whoſe office calles for more zeale now then did the former dayes, looke well into their office (if not ſo farre as to diſtaſt the ſame with <hi>Ionah</hi>) yet to have a more conſiderate regard, and to be more ſenſible of ſo ſacred and Angelicall a function, and not to prepare thereto (as the moſt doe) with myrth and Ioviality.</p>
               <p>Neither is my ſpeech wholly to theſe, a word of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would not doe amiſſe to the Prophets of God in earneſt, who having in ſinceritie vndertaken the calling, doe finde truly the burden of it.</p>
               <p>Let them not faint nor be diſcouraged, an end ſhall be, and their expectation ſhall not periſh for ever, though in the meane time they beare the heate and burden of the day, and the harveſt be great, and Labourers few.</p>
               <p>Let them take courage and grow yet bolder, to oppoſe againſt the face of all ſuch who caſt durt and diſhonour into the profeſsion.</p>
               <p>Let them not grow impatient with <hi>Ionah,</hi> though with him toſſed by ſea and land; the time is at hand wherein <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> our Archangel ſhall deſcend, cauſing them who have ſlept in the graves to awake, and they who have converted ſoules ſhall ſhine as the Starres in glory; but they who have ſubverted ſoules ſhall be turned into the darknes of Gehenna.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19643:23"/>
               <p> Thus farre have I beene bold with my brethren of the ſame profeſsion. I would be loath ſo to determine my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication (ſince the caſe of <hi>Ionah</hi> in the iuſtification of his anger againſt God, is not particular only to him, but may well be applyed as more generall and common.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Give me leave in the fourth place therefore to examine his words in a larger ſenſe, whether ever, either thee, or I, or any of vs have not beene in the exceſſe of this paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo farre miſ-carryed that in our perſons this ſpeech of <hi>Ionah</hi> be not too truly verified, I doe well to be angry againſt the Lord.</p>
               <p>It is to be wiſhed, that we were all in grace ſo well confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that Saint <hi>Iames</hi> doctrine were well grounded in vs; my brethren, count it all ioy when yee fall into divers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
               <p>But (as it is with vs) the exhortation of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is not needleſſe: Beloved thinke it not ſtrange concerning the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tryall, as if ſome new thing were happened to you.</p>
               <p>For iudgement muſt begin at the houſe of God; and hereat the righteous full oft-times proove diſmayed.</p>
               <p>Whether it be his owne ſinnes the waight whereof preſſe heavy, and he cries, yea roares and cannot be heard.</p>
               <p>Whether it be the iniquities of the times, as a man borne downe with a violent ſtreame; whether oppreſsion in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and violent perverting of iuſtice, able to make a wiſe man madde.</p>
               <p>Whether the ſcourge of tongues and malediction of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whether the ſecure eſtate of ſuch as feare not God, and the flouriſhing of ſcornes, a ſhrewd temptation, whether his owne neglected innocency or meekeneſſe trampled vnder, by the feet of the wealthy.</p>
               <p>Whether dereliction of friends, loſſe in eſtate, poverty, ſickeneſſe, or what other diſeaſe of the time.</p>
               <p>Or laſtly, <hi>Ionah</hi> his plague to ſuſtaine continuall moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his calling, and to be toſſed vp and downe.</p>
               <p>I doubt not but I have touched the grievances of many one, who heares mee this day: Hence come thoſe dolorous pangs, fearefull diſtempers, deſpairing cryes, thoſe fighes,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19643:23"/>thoſe groanes, that beating of the breaſt, that ſtamping with the foote, <hi>Ezekiels</hi> ſignes of mourning.</p>
               <p>In briefe, that curſing of the day of our nativities, and why were wee borne to ſuch hard conditions? O that the grave had beene my wombe, or the wombe alwaies great with mee. <hi>Non eſt dolor, ſicut dolor meus,</hi> No man ever ſo plagued, ſo troubled, ſo croſſed as I am, and I ſee no reaſon, no cauſe for all this, nor end of all my ſufferings.</p>
               <p>This to be the caſe of every of vs, who can deny ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other? and all this heate to be diſcharged, directly or indirectly againſt the face of God?</p>
               <p>The Lord doth ſend vs troubles many times to ſee how we will beare his yoke: but we are like a young Heifer or Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke vnaccuſtomed to the yoke, how oft have wee beene offended with our ſtate, our calling or condition?</p>
               <p>Behold Iſrael after the fleſh; why came wee into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe ſay they? why here is no water to drinke, why dyed we not in Aegypt? here's no bread to eate, no cloathes to put on, and now muſt we live vpon the bread of providence onely ſay we?</p>
               <p>We know God can provide ſuch things as are needfull in this life for his children, but why doth he not?</p>
               <p>He hath promiſed that no good thing ſhall be wanting to ſuch as feare before him, and ſeeke the righteouſneſſe of his kingdome.</p>
               <p>But wee ſee the contrary full often, wherefore is <hi>Lazarus</hi> laid at the rich mans doore to be releeved with his crummes? and <hi>Iob</hi> the richeſt man in the Eaſt, and one that feareth God too become poore even to a Proverbe?</p>
               <p>Why is <hi>Naboth</hi> moſt vniuſtly ſtoned and his field given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to an other? why is <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a good man caſt into priſon? and <hi>Ieremy</hi> an holy Prophet into the dungeon, and <hi>Daniel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lyons denne?</p>
               <p>Are theſe things done in a well ordered Common-wealth? now God ſeemes to take leſſe care in the behalfe of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then an indifferent King for his ſubiects.</p>
               <p>Sure, oppreſsion makes a wiſe man mad, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> and is not here iuſt cauſe of anger or elſe of Atheiſme?</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19643:24"/>
               <p> For is there not a God iudging the world? or if there be, why are not matters ordered in better faſhion then as we ſee?</p>
               <p>Caſt wee now our eyes vpon the wealthy ones of this world, and ſuch who care not for God; their eyes ſtare out with fatnes, and they doe even what they liſt ſaith <hi>David,</hi> their Tabernacles are ſafe from feare, neither is the rod of God vpon them ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> their Bull gendreth and faileth not, their Cow calveth and caſteth not her Calfe, they ſend forth their little ones like a flocke, and their children dance, they take the timbrell and harpe, and reioyce at the ſound of the Organe.</p>
               <p>This made <hi>David,</hi> to have beene almoſt of the ſame mind, as they, and to have caſt in his lot amongſt them. This very conſideration made <hi>Iob</hi> aſtoniſhed very much.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Ieremy</hi> could not forbeare, but he ſaith, Righteous art thou O Lord when I plead with thee, yet let mee talke with thee of thy iudgements. Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper, wherefore are all they happy that deale very treacherouſly?</p>
               <p>Thou haſt planted them, yea they have taken roote: they grow, they bring forth fruit, thou art neere in their mouth, and farre from their reines.</p>
               <p>Shall I proceed yet farther (to ſay nothing of the common broyles, which at this day, eate into the bowels of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the adverſaries of Zion prevailing and ſetting vp their banners for tokens.)</p>
               <p>How infinite might I be to reckon vp particulars wherein each man finds himſelfe aggrieved? for from him that weares the purple and the crowne, to him that is cloathed with a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen frocke, tribulation and diſtreſſe and anguiſh is vpon all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Syrach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why was I borne blinde ſaith one, and I borne deafe, and I borne lame ſaith a ſecond and a third, to bee a creeple, a ſcorne and deriſion to the world?</p>
               <p>No man content with his ſtate, but why was it ſo with me? why is it not otherwiſe with me? a company of wrangling pots are we thus to reaſon with the great Potter, thus to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill with our Maker, why haſt thou made mee thus? I like
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19643:24"/>this faſhion better then this, and why haſt thou not made me ſo? and doe we not oftentimes breake in the marring while we ſeeke to mend Gods making?</p>
               <p>O but the times are very badde, wherein we live, who can be patient to conſider well on it?</p>
               <p>We live in dogged dayes the laſt and worſt of times, wee ſeeke peace, but cannot obtaine it: O thou falſe tongue, what reward ſhall be given or done vnto thee thou falſe tongue? Woe is me that I am conſtrained to dwell in Meſech, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the tents of Kedar? O that I had the wings of a Dove? I would flye away, I would be gone. I ſaid I would make haſt to eſcape, becauſe of the ſtormes, winde and tempeſt, but becauſe I cannot, therefore is my ſoule vexed within me, and my heart within me is deſolate.</p>
               <p>Now beſides and beyond all this, what's our hope, what's our conſolation?</p>
               <p>The Lord hath promiſed to bring vs vnto an everlaſting reſt, an heavenly Canaan, but how ſhall we doe if he ſlay vs before we get thither? the ſea is before vs, the enemy behind vs with manifold diſcouraging impediments in this our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, <hi>Ogge</hi> the king of Baſan, the divell with his infernall le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and gates and barres of braſſe to keepe vs out.</p>
               <p>Why doth he leade vs about by the wilderneſſe, a long te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and dangerous iourney, ſince there is a farre more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way from Kadeſh Barnea, vnto the confines of Canaan the land of promiſe.</p>
               <p>Thus he workes by contraries ſtill. Why could not the Lord take vs preſently vnto his reſt without all this adoe, thinkes fleſh and blood? vnleſſe hee ſend vs into the ſea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, where already we have hardly eſcaped drowning.</p>
               <p>The billowes, o the roaring billowes! the waters of the ſea rage horribly, and we are horribly afraide, ſave Maſter, or we periſh.</p>
               <p>Thus he workes by contraries, we have here no continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Citie, but ſeeke one to come; we looke for walles and bulwarkes, but here are expoſed to all kinds of iniurious ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
               <p>We looke for ioy, but here is more cauſe of griefe; wee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19643:25"/>looke for peace, but here is paine; we looke for reſt, but here is none, for crownes and garlands, but behold, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, thornes and tribulations.</p>
               <p>In a word, hereafter we looke for an incorruptible body, a glorious body, a ſhining body; in the meane time we lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, we pine, we fret, we grieve, wee conſume, we dye, rotte in the grave, come to nothing; where's now our hope, where's now our conſolation?</p>
               <p>What? thinkes carnall reaſon, is this the way to light a candle, to put it out? is this way to attaine life, thorow death? to climbe heaven by deſcending firſt into hell? <hi>Ionah,</hi> why art thou angry? is there not cauſe? even of very deepe anger?</p>
               <p>For lay now all theſe things, or take but halfe into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, hath not the valianteſt hearted Chriſtian in theſe regards, cauſe to be offended, to proove impatient, and ſay with <hi>Ionah, yea, I doe well to be angry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So long as we be at reſt, and not tryed by temptations, there is no great neede of patience, no great diſcovery of impatience, vntill we be emptied from veſſell to veſſell, wee ſettle vpon our lees.</p>
               <p>But emptie the veſſell, ſhake the glaſſe, the lees or dregs which before were ſetled at the bottome doe now in great plentie ſhow themſelves.</p>
               <p>So when wee are ſhaken by temptations, O then how great infidelitie, how little faith, how much intemperancie, how little true zeale, how much anger, impatience and repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is diſcovered which before lay hidden in the bottome of our deceitfull hearts?</p>
               <p>For concluſion then of the doctrine, aske we the queſtion, ſo many as have felt the power of religion, this queſtion of our owne ſoules, whether ever in this ſenſe we have beene an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with God, (a proud conceit) yea I ſay againe, whether ever in this ſenſe we have beene angry with God or no.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> did not in plaine tearmes expreſſe ſo much, vntill the Lord, with whom is no diſſembling, did vrge and wring it from him.</p>
               <p>That whereby we are given to coniecture his diſpoſition
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19643:25"/>before the Lord ſpake, is in the words preceding, where it is ſaid, that <hi>Ionah</hi> fainted and wiſhed in himſelfe to dye, and ſaid it is better for mee to dye then to live.</p>
               <p>So that if at any time we faint and grow weary in the cauſe of Religion, or otherwiſe deſire and wiſh within our ſelves to be diſſolved only in regard of our preſent miſeries, which wee indure whatſoever they be, then take heede we fall not into the ſame guiltineſſe with <hi>Ionah</hi> here.</p>
               <p>Yea indeede we are already fallen too farre. For even theſe ſecret wiſhes of the ſoule, though not expreſſed outwardly, they have a kinde of language which God vnderſtands well enough, and wee are conſcious to our ſelues at the ſame time againſt God, of a certaine concealed anger: wherein whether wee doe well or ill, wee are for the preſent moſt vnfit Iudges, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lord for the moſt part of iniuſtice or wrong to our perſons and prayers, in our moſt ſecret imaginations.</p>
               <p>Yea wee are angry with that friend (though wee ſay not ſo much) in whom wee haue repoſed any truſt, if hee haue in any point dealt vnkindly with vs, if he have broken promiſe, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved vs, ſeparated from our diſtreſſe, much more if hee have wrought againſt vs, wee take it then moſt hainouſly: ſo when God, to our ſeeming, doth forget our miſery and troubles, to hide his face, and bee regardleſſe of vs, though wee have ſought him with many teares.</p>
               <p>When troubles daily doe ariſe, and of long continuance, yea and God himſelfe our onely friend doth ſeeme to arme himſelfe againſt vs, to make vs as a marke or Butte for his arrowes to aime at, (as <hi>Iob</hi> in his paſsion thought).</p>
               <p>Should God then (while the violence of the inward diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per laſteth) in the ſame manner aske the queſtion as to <hi>Ionah,</hi> wee would then goe neere hand to anſwer in the ſame manner as hee, yea <hi>I doe well to bee angry, angry euen to death.</hi> And ſo I deſcend vnto the third or laſt ſpecialty in <hi>Ionahs</hi> anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="aggravation">
               <head>3. His aggrauation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I doe well to bee angry even vnto death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere <hi>Ionah</hi> exceedes the iuſt meaſure of the queſtion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly conſidered.</p>
               <p>Indeede in no part of his anſwere he keepes good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the Lord; for though his ſpeech bee anſwerable to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19643:26"/>the parts of the demand, yet in no ſort is it agreeable with the will of the Demander.</p>
               <p>But here in this clauſe he ſhowes himſelfe irregular not only to Gods pleaſure or will, but alſo to the forme of the words from the Lord propoſed.</p>
               <p>For why elſe, as to the other parts of the demand (as when the Lord askes if he be angry, he ſaith, <hi>yea I am angry: Doeſt thou well to be angry? I doe well to be angry</hi>) ſo doth hee not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the laſt part accordingly? <hi>Doeſt thou well to bee angry for the Gourd, I doe well to be angry for the Gourd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which plainly ſhowes (as before is noted) that there were other farre greater cauſes then the Gourd, which forced theſe words from him, <hi>viz.</hi> whereas he ſaith, <hi>I doe well to bee angry, even vnto death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, it is a moſt intemperate ſpeech; and for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, reſpecting either the intention or effect of <hi>Ionah's</hi> anger.</p>
               <p>If we expound it of the intention, it then importeth thus much, that <hi>Ionah</hi> was exceeding angry, ſo angry that he was full bigge with anger, ſo bigge that he was ready to breake with anger; And if ſo, then fixe this <hi>Epitaph</hi> vpon his grave ſtone.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Here lyes the man, who did both raging Sea and Whale diſdaine:</l>
                  <l>His anger, worſe then Sea or Whale, his anger hath him ſlaine.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And why, yea why, ſhould not that anger which hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed many, in iuſtice turne the point ſometimes vpon that breaſt which bred it?</p>
               <p>Truly, the anger of <hi>Ionah</hi> in this place conceived, yea ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed againſt the Almighty, muſt needs be very great.</p>
               <p>For we are not angry with our ſuperiours, but for cauſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, ſuppreſsing commonly thoſe motions provoking to this paſsion towards them, which towards inferiours is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently expreſt.</p>
               <p>For example; that is tolerable in an equall, which is not to be borne with in a ſervant; that in a Lord, which not in a Knight; that in a Prince, which not in a Lord; that in a King, which not in a Prince; and laſtly, that is to be borne with patience from God Almighty, which is not to be brooked from any mortall creature beſides.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19643:26"/>
               <p> O then, when the heate of our anger aſcendeth thus high as to be angry not with Kings and Princes, and Potentates of the earth, but with the God of heaven, King of kings, and Lord over all lords; this is a fire that eates into the bones conſuming the marrow and the moiſture, and muſt wee not either burne in our owne cinders, or elſe daring to breake out, bee incountred and conſumed with that all devouring fire, that flame of Gods diſpleaſure, of his vnquenchable anger?</p>
               <p>Admire and wonder, that <hi>Ionah</hi> is angry with the great God, exceeding angry with the moſt puiſſant Lord, he telles this God and Lord ſo to his face; yet is not conſumed; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and wonder.</p>
               <p>But I doe rather vnderſtand it for the effect of <hi>Ionah's</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the effect conceived in a manner and ready for the birth, yet ſtrangled in the wombe, which had it beene brought forth, would vnto <hi>Ionah</hi> have brought moſt certaine death.</p>
               <p>In the old Law, he that curſed father or mother was to be put to death, much more he that ſhould curſe the Father of ſpirits, and great Creator of mankinde; this was expreſſely charged with preſent death, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Therefore wee reade, <hi>Naboth</hi> hath curſed God and the King, let him be ſtoned; therefore did <hi>Iobs</hi> wife tempt her husband to this ſinne; <hi>Curſe God and dye</hi> ſaith ſhee.</p>
               <p>This I conceive to be <hi>Ionah's</hi> caſe. He is come almoſt to the actuall ſinne of blaſphemie againſt the ſecond Perſon in the Trinitie, the which in thought he hath committed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
               <p>For he ſaith, he hath iuſt cauſe to be angry, and if he doe well to be angry, then ſure, God hath done him great wrong, and if ſo, why ſhould he not heare of it? yea though I dye for it, I will ſpeake my minde ſaith <hi>Ionah; For I doe well to be angry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We may ſupply the fuller meaning of <hi>Ionah's</hi> minde, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of <hi>Iob,</hi> and partly out of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> men ſubiect to the ſame paſsions, and wraſtling with the ſame aſſaults as here.</p>
               <p>They were both carryed away with this miſ-conceit, that God did vſe his power as a law, exerciſing herein, little better
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19643:27"/>then a Tyrannicall government, and therefore ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> in one place, is it good for thee that thou ſhould'ſt oppreſſe, &amp;c? and <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaith plainely, that the Lord by his great might or ſtrength did overbeare him, as is to be ſeene in the place before cited.</p>
               <p>Thus thinkes <hi>Ionah,</hi> and to this effect, hee reaſons in his over-caſt imaginations.</p>
               <p>My ſoule is even full of anxietie, and I want vtterance of my complaint. Thy hand is over powerfull for mee, thy counſels are vnſearchable, I know not what to ſay to it, this is the ſumme; I am weary of my life, for I ſee no fruite, no end of all my vexing labours.</p>
               <p>O yet, that God would grant mee this requeſt (before I open my lippes againſt the Holy one, and reproach my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and by mans law deſerve to be ſtoned) that hee would cut mee off and deſtroy mee, or hide mee in the grave. For ſure, I have moſt iuſt cauſe to be offended, yea ſure, <hi>I doe well to be angry, angry even to death,</hi> death to mee is better farre then life.</p>
               <p>I have touched (I ſuppoſe) vpon the higheſt ſtring of Saints impatiencie, wherevnto the perfecteſt of men, during yet their mortall condition, are moſt ſubiect; and beyond which is no remiſsion, but to fall into that ſinne vnpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, which holds no concord with Gods mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let</hi> vs now but make a cord to draw <hi>Ionah</hi> out of the pit, and preſerve all <hi>Ionaſſes</hi> from ſinking in this mire and mudde, and I will make the vſes and generall concluſion of the whole matter, ſpecially this ſecond generall part of <hi>Ionah's</hi> anſwer, and herein, the laſt ſpecially in this generall; the point yet in hand, <hi>Ionah's</hi> anger vnto death.</p>
               <p>The floods are riſen, O God, the floods are riſen might <hi>Ionah</hi> well here ſay, and all elſe brought vnto the ſame brinke of deſpaire or deſperate fury with <hi>Ionah</hi> here; O God, the floods are riſen, the floods O God have lift vp the waves.</p>
               <p>And this not ſo much in regard of the tyde of vngodlines flowing from without as the violent ſtreames of inraged an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from within: Save me, O God, for the waters are come in even into my ſoule.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19643:27"/>
               <p> Theſe, theſe are the waters which drowne the ſoule, to be feared more then thoſe waters which ſwallow vp the bodies of men.</p>
               <p>Now, two things there be which ſupport <hi>Ionah,</hi> and the one implies the other: one thing which the Lord doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, the other which he doeth worke, the one proceeding from his Mercy, the other from his Loue.</p>
               <p>Firſt, His Mercy it is which doeth cover <hi>Ionah's</hi> imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which at this time were riſen to a very great height. For how if the Lord ſhould have entred contention with thee <hi>Ionah?</hi> and ſet his anger againſt thine? what would have become of thee?</p>
               <p>The like may we ſay to <hi>Iob,</hi> to <hi>Ieremy;</hi> what <hi>Iob?</hi> doeth the Lord oppreſſe? Is it without reaſon, the Lords dealing ſo, and ſo with thee <hi>Ieremy? and doeſt thou well indeede to bee angry Jonah?</hi> dare wee thus to challenge the Holy one of Iſrael?</p>
               <p>O no; Take <hi>Ionah</hi> in his right temper, and he is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther minde, ſo is <hi>Iob,</hi> ſo is <hi>Jeremy:</hi> I ſaid I will no more make mention of thy name within my lippes ſaid <hi>Ieremy,</hi> in his heate he ſpake it, but a contrary ſtronger heate expelled that by and by, thy word was a fire ſhut vp within my bones, and I was weary with forbearing immediately after ſaith he.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Iob,</hi> Chap. 40. once have I ſpoken, yea twiſe, but I will ſay no more, I abhorre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes.</p>
               <p>But what marueile, if while the fit laſteth, the yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified fleſh take on? this being the beaſt which is to bee ſacrificed, vntill we be quite dead vnto our owne naturall deſires, reaſon and perverſe iudgement.</p>
               <p>This is that which the Lord in mercy paſſeth over, putting a difference here betweene <hi>Ionah</hi> and his anger, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſinnes of his children and his graces in them.</p>
               <p>So the words here according to the originall, are not to be read, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry?</hi> but thus, is it well that anger is with thee? according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle; It is not I that ſinne, but ſinne that dwelleth in me. This, as one day to be caſt out and quite aboliſhed from our natures, the Lord doth paſſe by, for the preſent accepting our perſons,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19643:28"/>not regarding the workes of our owne hands, but as we are his workemanſhip in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And this is the ſecond thing that preſerveth and vpholdeth <hi>Ionah,</hi> and with <hi>Ionah</hi> all Gods Elect in the moſt bitter conflicts from ſinking into the pit and finall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, namely, the hand and power of grace, which hath ſtated them in the covenant of Gods free Election, and doth ſuſtaine them in the ſame condition to their lives ends.</p>
               <p>For firſt, there is <hi>ſemen immanens,</hi> an abiding ſeede as <hi>John</hi> calles it, whereof whoſoever be quickened, never to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally loſe the life thereof, but the vertue thereof at all times remaineth, though not ſo evidently at all times diſcerned: even as the Starres in a darke night, are not ſeene to the eye; yet both the eye retaineth the power of ſeeing, and the Starres alſo are viſible in themſelves and abide fixed in the firmament, which the ſucceſsion of an other night plainly doeth diſcover.</p>
               <p>So in this caſe againe, and in this particular of anger, a Chriſtian is compared to a Philoſopher in a tempeſt at the Sea. While there is <hi>tumultus multus &amp; clamor magnus,</hi> Much tumult and clamour, the Philoſopher, though he be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Principles of his Art, at that time hath no abilitie of manifeſtation, neither himſelfe being at all diſpoſed, nor his hearers capable of inſtructions; ſo while the fury and ſtrength of temptation laſteth, the Chriſtian is not his owne man in appearance: waite then a while longer, the tempeſt will be over, the Starres ſhine cleere, and the eye of faith, ſhall be comforted with the light of Gods countenance.</p>
               <p>Now as there is evermore an habite of grace, and ſeede of God remaining in the ſoule of every true ſervant of God and faithfull member of Chriſt Ieſus, and ever ſhall remaine in ſpight of all the malice of Satan, and the gates of hell, and our owne corruptions too, and the rage of wicked men; ſo (for the operation of the ſame) it is at all times ſtirring, the power thereof, being never wholly buryed, even in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt agony of the ſoules vexation, there is a reſiſtance vnto evill, and a ſecret hand of grace running along with our impotent and tumultuous paſsions, keeping thoſe waving
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19643:28"/>ſtormes of the ſoule within ſome compaſſe, which elſe would ſwell above the bankes, to the fearefull inundation of the ſoules tranquillitie.</p>
               <p>And therefore is it (howſoever may ariſe rebelling com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions from within) yet never ſhall we finde that they have in direct tearmes of blaſphemy broken out contrary to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine light, inkindled in their breaſts, in deſpight againſt the Holy Redeemer; which too often falleth out in Caſt-awaies.</p>
               <p>Conſider the example before mentioned, whether <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Eliah,</hi> or <hi>Job,</hi> or <hi>Jeremy.</hi> It is true they were exceedingly and beyond meaſure tranſported to wiſh for death: and to curſe the day of their nativity doeth argue a great diſtemper of ſpirit; but it is but a diſtemper, and doth not forbid but they might (as ſoone after they were) be brought to a more ſober moode, and better minde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eliah</hi> wiſht to dye, ſo <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo <hi>Jonah</hi> here, wiſhes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt themſelves, howſoever their anger, or a great part thereof might be againſt the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremy</hi> they curſed, but whom? the Lord? no, they durſt not, they could not, therefore it breakes out an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way, and is diſcharged vpon the day, the night wherein they were conceived and borne, the pappes that ſuckled, knees that dandled them, the man that brought tydings; they ſhot at randome bitter words, yet none flye vpward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Maker, this caution ſtill hath beene remembred; and the ſecret power that hath curbed thoſe ſwelling moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hath at no time beene wanting to them.</p>
               <p>Two caſes there bee wherein I obſerve the holyeſt of Saints living, to be iniurious in the higheſt meaſure againſt their owne felicitie, but never directly againſt God: the one is in extremitie of their owne ſufferings, which hath now beene handled, the other an exceſſe of their zeale to Gods glory. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſhed to be wiped out of the booke of life, rather then that people ſhould have beene conſumed, to whom the Lord had made promiſe of entring Canaan.</p>
               <p>What would the nations have ſaid, thought he? either that the God of Iſrael was vniuſt of his word, or vnable of power to bring and plant, that people in the land of the poſſeſsion:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19643:29"/>O let me never ſee good day ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> rather then God ſhould ſuffer this diſhonour. With the ſame affectionate zeale was <hi>Paul</hi> mooved partly to his countrey-men, the Iewes of the ſame fleſh with him, chiefely in regard of Gods honour, who had ſworne and bound himſelfe in an everlaſting cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeede for ever, that rather then that people ſhould abſolutely be caſt off and forſaken, hee himſelfe might become Anathema and accurſed for ever.</p>
               <p>Doe you ſee by theſe examples, how iealous of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Saints have beene; though no mans zeale can be too great, to Godward, yet in the ardour thereof working with their dimme faith, to have diſcovered manifeſt impotency?</p>
               <p>The ſame effect, well nigh (to returne to the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) after a contrary manner of working in the violence of their owne extremities moſt commonly hath beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
               <p>There can no ſuch cauſes happen, wherein a man with <hi>Ionah</hi> ought to wiſh for death, the time by God appointed yet not come. <hi>Ionah,</hi> truly herein did tranſgreſſe, ſo did <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Eliah</hi> too.</p>
               <p>Yea, but to be angry with God in expreſſe tearmes, or to fall into this hopeleſſe exigent of curſing, can it any waies be excuſed, or made tolerable in the ſight of God or courſe of ſanctitie?</p>
               <p>What then ſhall we ſay for <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremy,</hi> or yet for <hi>Jonah</hi> the occaſion of this whole diſpute?</p>
               <p>Yea there is none ſo madde (I doe ſuppoſe) who will offer the excuſe or purgation of <hi>Ionah</hi> in this his madde teaſty combate and quarrell againſt the Lord his Maker, yet in this, will I exempt <hi>Ionah</hi> from the everlaſting curſe, in that hee fell not into expreſſe tearmes of curſing.</p>
               <p>For the other two, O what iuſt, what holy men! <hi>Iob</hi> I meane and the other good <hi>Ieremy,</hi> whether went ye downe? downe vnto the ſides of the pit? or how fell yee downe? downe into the bottome of the gulfe?</p>
               <p>For I am aſtoniſhed with <hi>Iobs</hi> three friends, when I behold his miſery, and I cannot but iudge him, as one ſhut vp in the pit, when I heare his words.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19643:29"/>
               <p> How commeſt thou out of the deepe O <hi>Iob?</hi> who ledde thee out of darkeneſſe into light o <hi>Ieremy?</hi> can a man live againe beeing once dead? even ſo are the fruits of your hopes, whoſe blaſted bloſſomes doe againe flouriſh, and your broken branches doe againe ſhoote out.</p>
               <p>O, the pit (I now well perceive, had not wholly ſhut her mouth vpon you, nor was the life of your hopes vtterly loſt, I muſt in this recall my ſelfe) for then (as the fire doeth reſiſt the water, the water the fire, as the divell is an enemie to our ſalvation, and heaven is oppoſite to hell) ſo they whom the God of heaven doeth caſt out as his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and they themſelves doe ſo iudge of themſelves to be perpetually reiected and abhorred of their Maker, the eſtate of theſe men will you know? or their condition, what it is?</p>
               <p>They are no longer men, but have put on the ſhapes of divels; for the image is quite changed from puritie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe which was in the creation, thus hath God loſt them, and they have loſt their part in God, God is now contrary to them, and they to God; as heate is to cold, as light is to darkeneſſe, life to death, fire to water.</p>
               <p>Thus God hates them, thus they hate God, thus God fights againſt them, they fight againſt God, <hi>Michael</hi> and his Saints and Angels, againſt the Divell his members and angels; and the enmitie it is immortall and never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</p>
               <p>They began firſt to perſecute God in his members, God in his turne powres the viall of his wrath vpon their heads, and they blaſpheme.</p>
               <p>God plagues them, they curſe God, and curſing are plagued, and plagued doe curſe continualy; this is the ſtate of the damned in hell, and this is all their ſpight againſt heaven.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſunke downe irrecoverably into the pit, the pit of fire and brimſtone hath ſhut her mouth vpon them, they are cloſed vp in the pit for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>But who will affirme, who dare to avouch, that thus it was with <hi>Iob,</hi> or his companyon <hi>Ieremy,</hi> or that to any of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19643:30"/>Gods Saints truely quickned by his grace in any of theſe meaſures it hath happened or can thus happen?</p>
               <p>No, For they never are at direct enmitie with God, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they may be brought to this point, through the force of continued grievances, to be confounded at Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to ſtagger in their mindes, and to incline to this ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, that it had beene better for them (whatever God may worke out of it, for his vnſearchable ends) yet for them and their parts, it had beene better not to have beene borne at all, then to be ordained to ſuch preſent wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; therevpon have they beene mooved to curſe not God, but their day, the night, the light and Starres (as before you have heard) any thing ſave only God, whoſe counſels they admire, though his iudgements proove diſtaſtfull.</p>
               <p>The matter will proove yet more cleere, if wee conſider and compare, but a little the contrary diſpoſition of ſuch, whom God hath given over to this fearefull ſinne.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Theſe doe reſiſt that light which for the preſent doth convince their iudgements; it fareth with the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Saints for the time, as with troubled waters, neither pleaſant to drinke, nor apt to render the true forme or proportion of any obiect therevnto preſented, their ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations are diſtempered, and their mindes like the Sunne with a cloude of errour overcaſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the outrage is diſcharged directly in the face of God, they diſgorge blaſphemies againſt heaven, as <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate threw his blood into the ayre againſt Chriſt; or the Thracians, who ſhot their arrowes vp to heaven in thunder and lightning, but the Saints divert the bent of their fury another way.</p>
               <p>Againe, thoſe doe it out of a deſpight and malice to the ſpirit of grace, in theſe it proceedeth from an impotency or infirmitie of their natures.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Saints doe evermore end with fairer light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, howſoever it may goe with them for the preſent, and they hang their harpes vpon the willow trees, they ſhall not alwaies live in Babylon, they ſhall returne to Sion, and their mouth ſhall be filled with laughter, and their tongues with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19643:30"/>Praiſe, in the meane time ſubiect to manifold alterations, as is the ſtate of all things in this world beſides.</p>
               <p>Now it ſhineth, anone tis overcaſt and clouded, now tis night, and now tis day, the ſeaſons of the yeere doe alter, there is Summer and Winter, Spring time and Autumne, ſo there is faire Weather, and foule Weather in the heart of a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>For now 'tis health and then 'tis ſickneſſe, now 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie and then adverſitie, now he ſings and then he ſighes, praiſe the Lord, ſing vnto the Lord faith <hi>Ieremy,</hi> curſed be the day wherein I was borne, immediately after ſaith the ſame <hi>Ieremy, Ionah</hi> is exceeding glad for the gourd, for one night, and is very weary of his life, the next morning.</p>
               <p>But conſider the vpright, and marke the end of the iuſt man ſaith <hi>David;</hi> for ſure the end of ſuch a man is peace at the laſt.</p>
               <p>Even as you may finde many complaints, and bitter cries mixed in the booke of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> what is the concluſion, or how end the laſt <hi>Pſalmes</hi> of that booke? their beginning commonly and ending is this, praiſe the Lord, praiſe yee the name of the Lord.</p>
               <p>But what's the end of ſinners more ſpecially of ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? woundes and death, and blood-ſhed, knives and rackes and halters, ſnares, fire and brimſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt, horrours and terrours, death and damnation.</p>
               <p>For theſe are they that blaſpheme God, and really curſe his holy name, vpon theſe he powreth the vials of his wrath, and they gnaw their tongues, and blaſpheme and repent not.</p>
               <p>There is a word cloathed about with death ſaith <hi>Syrach,</hi> but it is not found in the habitations of <hi>Iacob,</hi> there is a ſinne vnto death ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> I ſay not that yee ſhould pray for it ſaith he, but this he ſaith, we know that every one that is borne of God ſinneth not, that ſinne, but he that is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God, keepeth himſelfe pure, and that wicked one toucheth him not, albeit with <hi>Jonah</hi> he may be angry, albeit in the ſtrength of his malady, hee may curſe life, and wiſh death, yea never to fall into that ſinne of death.</p>
               <p>Thus have we performed a worke of love, to draw <hi>Ionah</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19643:31"/>out of the ditch, and have preſerved all <hi>Ionaſſes</hi> from the like danger of ſinking.</p>
               <p>What remaineth but the concluſion only? and it ſhall be briefely folded vp in a few concluſions or generall vſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from this which hath beene ſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And the Firſt ſhall be a point of exhortation, and this to the Saints of God, moleſted in this their mortall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with varietie of temptations, and of paſsions, that they may learne the way to peace, and when they finde by the pulſe of their affections, a ſtrong inclination to <hi>Ionah's</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, they may vſe theſe remedies to allay the fury, and ſettle the tranquillitie of their owne ſoules.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let them conſider againſt whom they doe oppoſe in their anger, is it not againſt the great and mighrie God? The Thiſtle in Lebanon, ſent to the Cedar in Lebanon, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, give thy daughter to my ſonne to wife, or take thou my daughter to thy ſonne to wife, and there paſſed by a wilde beaſt that was in Lebanon, and trode downe the Thiſtle: Thus ſaid <hi>Joaſh</hi> King of Iſrael to <hi>Amaziah</hi> King of Iudah, when he ſent this meſſage, let vs looke one another in the face, and this is the leaſt of a thouſand that I can ſay, when we dare provoke the God of heaven to his face.</p>
               <p>Can we throw downe mountaines by our might, or dry vp the ſea at our rebuke? Can the Toade (as the Fable hath it) equall the Elephant in bigneſſe, though ſhee ſwell, and ſwell, and ſwell againe, and burſt in ſwelling?</p>
               <p>O then let vs remember that arrowes ſhotte vp into the ayre, returne vpon the head of the ſhooters, and pierce downewards.</p>
               <p>Againe, conſider thine owne deſerving, for ſure thou haſt good cauſe to be angry with God and why? thou haſt from time to time ſo well deſerved at his hands.</p>
               <p>It is the mercy of the Lord that we are not all conſumed ſaith <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and truly wee are leſſe then the leaſt of all his mercies, therefore the vſe is ſoveraigne which the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet maketh, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3. Wherefore doeth a living man complaine, a man for the puniſhment of his ſinnes? Let vs ſearch and try our waies, and turne againe to the Lord;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19643:31"/>Let vs lift vp our heart with our hands, vnto God in the heavens, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, (to paſſe from this) iudge not of Gods favour to thee, or his righteous proceedings in thy cauſe or perſon, from the ſenſe of thy preſent ſuffrings, but from the end and iſſue which commonly God makes of his Saints afflictions: and therefore whereas now thou art vnder, and thy feete ſticke faſt in myre and clay, pray vnto God with <hi>David,</hi> that he would advance thy head, and ſet thee vpon the rocke which is higher then thou; ſo ſhalt thou be able to looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee round, and with comfort behold the hilles, and dales, ſpacious forreſts and groves, thou ſhalt then (with correction of thy paſſed folly) perceive plainely the cauſes, the reaſons, the end, iſſue of Gods wiſe and gracious procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with thee, and perceiving ſhalt praiſe and magnifie his name for it.</p>
               <p>The Warre-like Souldier, while the heate of the battell laſteh, heares and ſees nothing but confuſed noiſe and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rolled in blood, the pranſing of ſtrong horſes, the ratling ſpeares, Bellonaes rage with the claſhing armes, and clanging trumpe, doth aſtonne his ſenſe for the preſent, and hee hath no leiſure ſo long, to thinke of the countrey of Peace, the Enſignes of Honour, the Garlands of Victory. Victorious when he doth returne from the ſpoyle of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, then he rides in the Chariot of Triumph; Trophees are erected, he doth with ioy recount his dangers paſſed, glory in his wounds received, when all tongurs doe ſound his praiſes: <hi>Saul</hi> hath ſlaine his thouſand, and <hi>David</hi> his ten thouſand.</p>
               <p>Even ſo when the Warre-fare appointed for vs, is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, we ſhall ſtand vpon Mount Sion, Victorious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Aegyptians dead vpon the ſhoore, and ſhall ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Horſe and his ryder are throwne into the Sea; Principalities, and Powers are vanquiſhed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and we ſhall raigne for evermore.</p>
               <p>Secondly, My ſecond vſe ſhall be alſo of exhortation, but this to the troublers of Sions peace, and Edoms children who inſult vpon her deſolations.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19643:32"/>
               <p> It is neceſſary ſaith our Saviour, that offences come, but woe be to them who are the cauſers, and grieve the ſoules of Gods children, for they doe not alwaies labour of their owne inward griefes, and private diſtreſſes of their owne ſoules from within, <hi>Eliah</hi> flyes from the face of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> and growes weary of his life, woe be to <hi>Iezabel</hi> therefore, who is the cauſe of it.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the Saints groane and cry out for the wrongs done vnto them, and grow impatient of ſpirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord doeth not worke the deliverance, ſhall we ſay (howſoever their impatiencie is not to bee excuſed) that the world who hath procured their vnreſt, ſhall eſcape vnpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? or that the ſoules ſhall not be heard, who to this day cry from vnder the Altar, how long o Lord, holy and true, doeſt thou not iudge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</p>
               <p>Remember the parable of the widow, and vniuſt Iudge, avenge me of mine adverſary ſaith ſhee, avenge mee of mine adverſary, and ſtill ſhee cryeth, avenge mee of mine adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, he would not for the iuſtneſſe of her cauſe heare her, but her importunity prevailed.</p>
               <p>What's the vſe our Saviour makes thereof? the anſwere ariſeth by a gradation, ſhall not God much more Iudge and revenge, who is a iuſt Iudge, and in a moſt iuſt and rightfull cauſe, and that in the behalfe of his children, his children which doe not onely call, but cry, and cry, day and night? ſhall not God avenge his owne elect, ſaith he, which cry day and night vnto him, though hee beare long with them? As who would ſay, there is no ſenſe nor reaſon to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore he ſaith plainly, I tell you, he will avenge them ſpeedily, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In the third place; Let vs learne to bee adviſed of this one thing, how wee ſpend our iudgements vpon any whom we yet ſee labouring vnder the croſſe; leaſt prooving vncharitable in our cenſure, it proove to be our turne next to vndergoe the ſame tryalls, vnder which wee ſee our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome bitterneſſe of ſpirit wraſtling for the preſent.</p>
               <p>Alas, If we iudge onely from the outward behaviour and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19643:32"/>externall effects, which for the preſent affect our ſenſes, <hi>Ionah</hi> then is already condemned by our doome, and how hardly muſt it goe with all thoſe famous Worthies before named?</p>
               <p>Rather, Let vs enter into this account with our ſelves, and ſay, good God, if <hi>Ionah</hi> indued with a farre greater meaſure of holineſſe then poore I, did proove thus fretfull and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient vnder the hand of God, how leſſe able ſhould I have beene to have borne but halfe the burden he ſuſtained?</p>
               <p>If <hi>Eliah, Moſes, Ieremy, Iob,</hi> had not the power to maſter their vnruly paſsions, ſure then, if Ibe not conſcious to my ſelfe of the like weakeneſſe, I never came vnto the tryall, or how weakely ſhould I reſiſt in the day of evill?</p>
               <p>A man that lyes groveling on the ground, and ſends forth lamentable groanes, wee know not well the anguiſh of his ſpirit, yet this we know, that he is terribly indiſpoſed, yet for all this (though the ſight of all men, and in his owne thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king too, he be as a man moſt deſperately forlorne and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable) he may notwithſtanding by the helpe of ſome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Phyſitian and Chirurgion be recovered and ſet vpon his legs againe.</p>
               <p>This comes to paſſe more ordinarily in the diſeaſes of the ſoule, then in the diſtempers of the body.</p>
               <p>The more bitter bee the words of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and the more extreamely we heare <hi>Ionah</hi> to take on, the more deepely let vs iudge of them, that they have drunke of the cuppe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, the bitter cup of worme-wood and gall.</p>
               <p>And this I finde God himſelfe to have taken notice of, and in a tender regard and compaſsionate feeling of her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, thus to comfort his poore diſtreſſed Church by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Awake, awake, ſtand vp O Ieruſalem, which haſt drunke at the hand of the Lord, the cuppe of his fury, thou haſt drunke the dregs of the cup of trembling and wrung them out.</p>
               <p>A man in drinke (we vſe to ſay) is not himſelfe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I finde added in the ſame place, and with it I conclude the point.</p>
               <p>Heare now this, thou afflicted and drunken but not with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19643:33"/>wine, thus ſaith the Lord, the Lord and thy God, that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the cauſe of his people, Behold, I have taken out of thine hand, the cup of trembling, even the dregges of the cuppe of my fury; thou ſhalt no more drinke it againe, but I will put it into the hand of them that afflict thee, which have ſaid to thy ſoule, bow downe that we may goe over, and thou haſt laide thy body as the ground, and as the ſtreete to them that goe over.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, But now laſtly, let mee adde the concluſion of the whole matter, what's the concluſion of this whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, contention or conteſtation betweene the Lord and <hi>Ionah?</hi> A Song of praiſe, a Meditation of due thankfulneſſe, Bleſſe the Lord o my ſoule, and all that is within mee, bleſſe his holy name.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe the Lord o my ſoule and forget not all his benefits, who forgiveth all thine iniquities, who healeth all thy diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who redeemeth thy life from deſtruction, might <hi>Jonah</hi> well ſay, and crowneth thee with loving kindneſſe and tender mercies, let every one, who hath taſted the ſame cup with <hi>Ionah,</hi> conſeſſe.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Ionah,</hi> how great was thy offence! how heavy <hi>Ionah</hi> was thy anger? wherefore came not thy ſaying to paſſe? or why did not death prevent thy wiſh, ſince thou thoughteſt it no ſinne to be angry with God? had it not beene too light a recompence for this thy rebellion, to have ſent thee haſtily quicke into the grave with thy ſinnes vpon thy head?</p>
               <p>Behold, death even called for, doeth not appeare, the Lord is more mercifull to <hi>Ionah,</hi> then <hi>Ionah</hi> to himſelfe; man is angry with God, God is not angry with man. What ſhall we ſay?</p>
               <p>The caſe is not <hi>Ionah's</hi> alone, O <hi>David,</hi> how troubled doeth the courſe of many of thy <hi>Pſalmes</hi> runne? why doeſt thou forget mee o God? why art thou abſent from the the words of my complaint o God? Awake o Lord, ſtand vp and iudge my quarrell.</p>
               <p>Thus ſpeakes <hi>David,</hi> and much more, as a man not well pleaſed with his God, and as though the Lord were aſleepe or deafe, or blinde, or forgetfull, as if hee would not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19643:33"/>or could not regard the cauſe that was equall.</p>
               <p>Yea but this ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> at other times hath recollected himſelfe from this errour, and hath as plainly noted the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Lords more gracious and louing dealing both with himſelfe and all Gods childrenels.</p>
               <p>For hee knoweth whereof wee bee made ſaith hee in the Pſalme before cited, he well vnderſtands our frame, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth that we are but duſt, therfore like as a father pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne children, ſo the Lord pittieth them that feare him, and ſhall ſet our ſinnes as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt.</p>
               <p>Therfore alſo ſayth another Prophet ſpeaking in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God, I will not contend for euer neither will I be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies wroth: For the ſpirit ſhould faile before me and the ſoules which I haue made.</p>
               <p>For the iniquity of his covetouſneſſe was I wroth and ſmote him, I hid me and was wroth and he went on frowardly in the way of his heart.</p>
               <p>I have ſeene his waies and will heale him, I will lead him alſo and reſtore comforts vnto him and to his mourners, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 57.</p>
               <p>Here is the goodneſſe of our God and the whole worke of our ſaluation; this is his glory which he will not impart to others, nor to our merits or any deſert in vs, (for we are a froward and moſt vntoward generation in our ſelues).</p>
               <p>And this is the whole benefit he expects at our hands the calves of our lippes, and herevnto he hath ordained vs in his beloved before the foundation of the world, that wee ſhould render vnto him the ſacrifice of praiſe, a thankfull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement from the ground of our hearts: Bleſſe ye the Lord, as before.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe is it that the Saints in glory (whoſe felicity in part is ſhadowed by thoſe foure and twenty elders. <hi>Reu.</hi> 4) fall downe before him that ſirs on the throne, and worſhip him that liveth for ever and ever, and caſt their crownes before the throne, (as acknowledging their owne vnworthyneſſe) but thus they ſay.</p>
               <p>Thou art worthy O Lord to receive glory and honour
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19643:34"/>and power; for thou haſt created all things and for thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they are and were created.</p>
               <p>Sing we vnto the Lord a new ſonge, for old things are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and all things are made new, a new heaven and a new earth, a new Ieruſalem from aboue.</p>
               <p>And old things are cleane paſſed away, for there ſhall bee no more ſorrow nor crying nor paine ſaith S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> there ſhall be likewiſe no longer infirmity nor diſeaſe of minde nor body, there ſhall not be thoſe vexations nor yet thoſe vexing cauſes which here we both meete and carry about with vs.</p>
               <p>The tempter cannot reach vs there, temptations ſhall be baniſhed for euer. Anger hath no place in heauen: <hi>Ionah,</hi> thy branch ſhall flouriſh and thy gourd it ſhall not wither, the Sea ſhall not toſſe thee, the whale ſhall not eat thee, the Sun ſhall not ſmite thee, the fire ſhall not burne thee.</p>
               <p>Who then can be angry or euill affected when God ſhall ſhew himſelfe moſt willing to pleaſe vs? when he ſhall make all things, worke for our contentment?</p>
               <p>O Lord I am aſhamed now ſaith <hi>Ionah,</hi> when I conſider this thy moſt wonderfull goodneſſe, I doe repent of this my fooliſh anger and begin to waxe exceeding angry, that euer I was mooued to anger againſt ſo good ſo mercifull ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a redeemer, who doeſt not onely paſſe by our offences when we haue moſt hainouſly prouoked thy iuſt diſpleaſure, but haſt alſo reſerved &amp; laid vp in ſtore for vs moſt vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wretches, ſuch good things as paſſe mans imagination to conceive.</p>
               <p>O Lord God mercifull and gracious, long ſuffring &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant in goodneſſe and truth, accompliſh thy good word vnto thy ſervants and ſhew vs thy glory, that we may live and never dy that we may live and praiſe thee eternally. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <p>NOw, to call thee backe a little, friendly Reader, to the matter of my text, and withall, if I may perſume to communicate my ſelfe vnto thy good nature, I would intreat thee for the Author thus to iudge.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19643:34"/>
               <p> That he fell not by his hap-hazard vpon his text, or that hee hath not had a feeling of the ſame. What learning call you that which doth carry in hir boſome a ſenſe or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of hir knowen principles? It hath the name of <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge experimentall,</hi> which cannot be attained by all the ſearch of meere ſtudy, and is to bee preferred before all humane learning acquired by the documents and precepts of men.</p>
               <p>Who can deſcribe the image of God the father, or pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray out the ſhape of the holy Ghoſt, or expreſſe the glory of the bleſſed Trinity? The meaneſt Chriſtian who hath God in his heart doth retaine a ſounder knowledge of his maker by thoſe hidden operations felt within, then the ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Philoſopher in the height and ſublimity of his ſoring ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, or thoſe better learned clearkes; who can diſpute ſubtilly aboue the Trinity, yet want power to pleaſe the holy Trinity.</p>
               <p>O but that knowledge is full of danger my text ſpeaks of, and who would wiſh to be poſſeſſed with ſuch a feeling as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> was? not I, not thou, nor any man; yet take heede, thou maieſt be over-raſh in iudging. For why? anger doeth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and that ordinarily preſuppoſe love. O fearefull caſe, is <hi>Ionah</hi> angry with God, ſaiſt thou? an other is of this minde, is it poſsible in a fraile man, to conceive anger againſt the great God? whence ſprings this familiarity betweene heaven and earth? <hi>aut quam nuper è coelo deſcendiſti Ionah,</hi> how lately cameſt thou out of heaven <hi>O Ionah?</hi> yea ſure, by the very nature of the ſpeech muſt be implyed a certaine intercourſe of favour and loving commerce betweene the heavenly God and vs. Why els is any man angry with his fellow, but in a conceyt that he hath bin requited euill for good, and the fruits of hate where hee looked for the effects of loue?</p>
               <p>Why then, euen hence in like manner ariſe thoſe manifold heart-burnings and great diſturbances of the Saints quiet; ſince they have bin aſſured of Gods love, but want all ſignes thereof in their diſtreſſes. Is this the part of a loving father think his misbeleeving children, to neglect their ſuites who call day and night vnto him? what's become of his promiſes and thoſe mervailous workes our forefathers have told vs of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19643:35"/>wherefore doth he not ariſe and helpe vs and that early? O my God, I cry in the day time and thou heareſt not, and and in the night ſeaſon alſo my ſoule refuſeth comfort. Here our faith begins to ſtagger, for what? hath God forgotten to be gracious, and will he be no more intreated, and is his mercy cleane gone for evermore?</p>
               <p>Then the ſpirit is almoſt tyred with waiting, and the fleſh growes monſtrous vnruly. God is not ſo good as his word, for he hath promiſed, if in trouble we call vpon him, he will helpe vs, but he regards neither our calling, nor cryes, nor teares. O now the ſpirit waxeth hot, and the blood doth boyle within the veines: and thus our anger ariſeth againſt God, a thing not impoſsible, as you ſee, nor yet allowable, to the Saints moſt incident, and to the beſt of Saints, more ordinarily then to the worſt of hypocrites, or any other to the ſtate of grace not yet called.</p>
               <p>Indeede, for theſe, I doe not reade of many, or any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in this kinde, to have entred Conteſtation with the Lord, as <hi>Ionah</hi> here hath done, nor is it the <hi>Nabals</hi> of the world, but the <hi>Davids</hi> who mourne in their prayer, and are vexed. For vpon what grounds can they challenge God of his promiſe, and expoſtulate? where hath God bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto theſe with an oath, that he will be their God, and of their ſeede for ever? how oft have they called vpon him in faith, and wept vnto him in zeale? what love to his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, what truſt to his Word, what aſſurance of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, what conſolation in his promiſes, hath beene at any time in their hearts reſiding?</p>
               <p>I am not angry with the Sunne when it ſhineth to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes, nor with the Starres, becauſe they runne round; I am not angry with the Windes at Sea, when my houſe by fire is burnt at home; or laſtly, why ſhould the Malefactor, who cryes guiltie at the Barre, be angry with the Iudge, who gives ſentence according to the law vpon his offence?</p>
               <p>Even ſo truly, the wicked fooliſh, who ſay in their hearts there is no God, and doe impute their good and bad hap to blinde chance or fortune, who are men of an other world, and ſtrangers to godlineſſe: I ſee no reaſon their anger ſhould
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19643:35"/>reach, whether their beleefe doth not. Yea truly when they are haled before Gods iudgement Seat, as Malefactors ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, their guiltie conſciences proclaime woe immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but then begins their anger and deſperate rage, when the ſcalding plagues of Gods wrath doe begin to torment their bodies, and the horrour of deadly darkeneſſe doth ceaſe vpon their ſoules for their wilfull blindneſſe and folly, and their rage is not only againſt God, but in a remarkeable kinde of iuſtice, againſt their owne members, they gnawed their tongues and blaſphemed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>But if their malice breake out againſt God or his Saints ſooner (as oft it doth) it is then a fearefull preparation to theſe eternall woes mentioned, and hath more properly the name of malice then of anger. For what difference is there betweene the anger of Gods Saints, and of his enemies? even ſuch as I have ſhewed, as is the anger betweene two friends, and two moſt contrary enemies.</p>
               <p>Theſe things (gentle Reader) I have more deepely ſearcht into by occaſion of my Text, not that I preſume herein to commend vnto thee any rare point of skill: for that which may fall out to be rare in the courſe of my ſtudies may have beene more ſoundly noted in the labours of other men, and perhaps is not new vnto thy iudgement; nor to this end doe I it, to commend the feeling of this knowledge vnto any, not ſo farre experimented in this kinde of learning which wee have from <hi>Ionah;</hi> but to this end rather, that wee may bee wiſe to put a difference, and be ſuſpended from raſh iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the ſtate of divers Gods Elect, wraſtling here in this vale of miſery, falling and riſing, foyled, and ſometimes foyling like prevailers, and that herein we ſtudie true thankfulneſſe to the ſole-worker of our ſalvation, who preſerveth the ſoules of his Saints from going downe into the pit of deſperation.</p>
               <p>For my ſelfe (Chriſtian Reader) I was angry with my God, and knewit not; very angry but did not well conſider it. How manifold are thy tryalls? O how various and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull art thou in the exerciſing of vs thy fraile creatures? <hi>Vſque quo Domine, vſque quo,</hi> ſhal not my griefes and groanes,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19643:36"/>my deepe ſighings and often teares, and ſtrong cryes, be full effectuall in thy fight, to manifeſt thy power within, to vtter thy praiſe abroad? O thoſe hills of peace, where are they? why haſt thou cauſed me to hope in thy word &amp; haſt nor fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht me vnto the battel? why was I called —? but returne now vnto thy reſt, O my ſoule, and hope yet confidently. I was angry and mourned in my prayer and was vexed: was it not in thy temple, O God, in thy temple that my ſoule was exceedingly caſt downe and troubled? in thy temple there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I praiſe thee, becauſe there thou ſpakeſt peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my troubled ſoule, and did'ſt allay the heat of all my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented paſsions, ſaying as ſometime thou didſt vnto thy ſervant <hi>Ionah, Doeſt thou well to be angry?</hi> Thus, even thus thou rebukedſt the windes and the waves of all my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward commotions, and there followed immediately a great calme, praiſe the Lord O my ſoule and all that is within me praiſe his holy name. For it was not fleſh nor blood then which then was in the ſtrength of impariency and ſtamped with the foot, it was not fleſh and blood that did reveale, that did put this good motion into my breaſt, but my father in heaven, therefore praiſe the Lord O my ſoule.</p>
               <p>At this time I was aſsigned to the Croſſe, &amp; had not yet cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the Text I meant to treat of: the choiſe was ſoone made; For what more acceptable ſervice to our God, more pleaſing to his Church, more effectual for the preachers of his word to deale in, then to expreſſe their minds vpon thoſe Themes, the power whereof hauing firſt ſubdued their owne affections doth with greater force from them flow forth vnto others, and procure more ample glory to his name, vnto whom the whole action and efficacy of the worke is in ſpeciall wiſe to be referred.</p>
               <p>Thus have I made my ſelfe a foole in glorying, but it is in my infirmityes, and if for this I be diſdained of the <hi>Michals</hi> of the world, I will ſtudy to become yet viler in their eyes, that Gods power by my weaknes may be exalted. Is not this the end of all our beings? and ought we not by all meanes whether by precept or example or however labour here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? whether we be beſides our ſelues ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19643:36"/>
                  <hi>Corinthians</hi> it is to God, or whether wee bee ſober it is for your cauſe and hee is no follower of <hi>Paul</hi> as hee followed Chriſt in this, who will not thus indeavour to become all things to all men, that of all ſorts he may gaine ſome to God and he that reſpecteth his owne credit private opinion and ſpeeches of others, before the winning of ſouls, he is aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt; a ſhame of all others moſt ſhamefull and one moſt vnworthy to be a miniſter of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Thus Chriſtian and friendly Reader and one of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith whoſe love I doe onely imbrace, have I not made my ſelfe ſtrange vnto thee, and for this cauſe deſire the fruit of thy prayes to be aſsiſtant vnto me that I may open my mouth with boldneſſe in the cauſe of the Goſpel wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I have traviled and am yet in paine. I beleeved and therefore did I ſpeake ſaith <hi>David,</hi> but I was ſore greived. I alſo beleeved, the ſame have I preached, the ſame againe have I penned. Now to all thoſe who love the Lord Ieſus, I conclude, Grace be vnto them, and Mercy, and vpon the Iſrael of God.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
